<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
	<atom:link href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/</link>
	<description>CANCER &#124; April 25–27, 2016</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2016 12:40:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.18</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Day Three Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/day-three-highlights/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 16:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights of the Day Day Three of the World Medical Innovation Forum was short, but was filled with some of the most exciting aspects of the meeting. The first session touched on the needs of cancer patients who require alternative strategies to achieve optimal therapeutic benefit, and the advantages and challenges associated with combination therapy. <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><img src="http://image.s6.exacttarget.com/lib/fe8f127274650d797c/m/1/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160427_1732-150-HEADER.jpg" alt="WMIF Header" /></strong></p>
<h2>Highlights of the Day</h2>
<p>Day Three of the World Medical Innovation Forum was short, but was filled with some of the most exciting aspects of the meeting. The first session touched on the needs of cancer patients who require alternative strategies to achieve optimal therapeutic benefit, and the advantages and challenges associated with combination therapy.</p>
<p>The opening session was followed by a fireside chat with Joseph Jimenez, CEO of Novartis, who provided insight into Novartis&#8217; successes and discussed current topics including CRISPR, CAR-T, a second generation of immuno-oncology, and the biggest threats to the future of innovation.</p>
<p>The morning continued with a session in which panelists discussed new cancer diagnostics driven by advances in genetics, genomics and proteomics, and the integration of these technologies into the delivery of care. This panel was followed by a discussion around the evolving role of disease-focused philanthropic foundations in patient care. For more in-depth highlights from Day Three, see below.</p>
<p>The capstone event of the Forum was the announcement of the <a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=fc8c9e0c70cd2e56edd5b51f67c06c849eec650f884e68e52cb45eb35ed3fe5b">Disruptive Dozen</a>, the 12 technologies predicted to have the greatest impact on cancer care in the next decade. The main stage was filled with 12 influential leaders in cancer research and clinical care from Massachusetts General Hospital, Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, who came together for an exciting and insightful discussion around these state-of-the-art medical technologies and what they mean for the future of the field.</p>
<p>The Forum closed with notes from Anne Klibanski, MD, Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, who noted that one of the greatest accomplishments of the Forum was the facilitation of a new community; a community that can shift paradigms and accelerate cures by having open dialogue, understanding priorities, and incorporating patient needs, expectations, and quality of life issues, and posed a challenge to the audience to maintain this dialogue even after conclusion of the meeting.</p>
<p>Next year, the Forum will focus on cardiovascular disease and will be held from May 1-3, 2017 at the Westin Copley in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
<p><img src="http://image.s6.exacttarget.com/lib/fe8f127274650d797c/m/1/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160427_1732-150-2.jpg" alt="2016 World Forum" /></p>
<h2>New Philanthropy: Patients Driving Innovation</h2>
<p>As part of continued discussion around patient-driven innovation, the New Philanthropy session provided insight into the efforts of philanthropic leaders and how their community is redefining its role to develop new ways to help patients and drive breakthroughs. As disease foundations become more involved in all aspects of patient care, including the lab, clinic, engagement, and regulatory approval process, their role has evolved.</p>
<p>As gaps in funding for basic and translational research grow, these organizations have provided extensive financial support to the cancer research community, which has led to the development of breakthrough therapies and promising technologies. As Louis DeGennaro, PhD, President and CEO of the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society, pointed out their foundation funded the basic research that eventually led to the development of Gleevec and supported early efforts in the development of CAR-T technology at the University of Pennsylvania. Additionally, Judy Salerno, MD, President and CEO of Susan G. Komen for the Cure, emphasized the importance of funding young investigators and remarked that, as funding has dried up, we are starving a pipeline of next-generation investigators who are needed to advance progress.</p>
<p>To provide this support, fundraising is essential, and the panel discussed the role of athletic events and social media in driving their efforts. As Dr. DeGennaro observed, cancer patients &#8220;want to win,&#8221; and athletic events such as walks, challenges, and races are a practical manifestation of that desire and are successful because &#8220;people give to people.&#8221; Supporting that notion, Billy Starr, Founder and Executive Director of the Pan-Mass Challenge, added that today&#8217;s technology allows people to reach out to their world and create bonds and opportunities that are distinct from the impact of direct mail or celebrity spokespeople. When asked about the influence of the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge and whether they would consider that type of engagement for their audiences, Judy Salerno, MD, President and CEO of Susan G. Komen for the Cure, noted that their focus tends to be more directed toward the recruitment and development of people who are passionate about their mission and can become advocates.</p>
<p>To push for faster cures, panelists noted that their organizations are facilitating ongoing dialogue between patients and the FDA to address issues, concerns, and preferences, and training advocates in science to better disseminate their message. Additionally, as money raised from the Pan-Mass Challenge is donated exclusively to treatment and research at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Mr. Starr also noted the patient role in the design of the Yawkey Center for Cancer Care, which was intended to advance clinical care and enhance the patient experience.</p>
<h2>Disruptive Dozen</h2>
<p>After rigorous consideration by cancer faculty from the Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital, and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, the 12 technologies that are predicted to have the greatest impact on cancer care in the next decade were announced. After a short audio clip describing their disruptive technology, panelists representing each of the 12 areas enlightened the audience as to why their respective fields would have an impact on the future of cancer care in a series of sound bites.</p>
<p>Following a major theme of the Forum, and perhaps unsurprisingly, cellular immunotherapy was announced as the most disruptive technology for the next decade. Marcela Maus, MD, PhD, Director of Cellular Immunotherapy at MGH, highlighted the promise of this technology by stating that it has the potential to become a frontline cancer therapy and noting the unprecedented results seen in some patient populations thus far. However, she also noted that there are obstacles to overcome in the development of this technology for the treatment of solid tumors, which can be addressed by identifying new targets, using different engineering strategies to distinguish tumor from self, and targeting the tumor microenvironment.</p>
<p>The second runner-up for most disruptive technology was liquid biopsy for oncology, and Shyamala Maheswaran, PhD, Associate in Molecular Biology, Surgery at MGH, praised the benefits of more frequent, less invasive sampling methods as compared to tumor biopsy and described the applications of this technology in early detection of cancer, monitoring of therapy, evaluation of mutational status to direct therapeutics, and assessment of heterogeneity between tumor cells for a deeper understanding of tumor evolution.</p>
<p>Coming in at number seven, genome editing was represented by Keith Joung, MD, PhD, Associate Chief of Pathology for Research at MGH. When posed the question, &#8220;how crisp are CRISPRs?&#8221; by Forum Co-Chair Daniel Haber, MD, PhD, Director of the MGH Cancer Center, Dr. Joung explained that, while limiting off-target effects at this time is a challenge, we have a distinct opportunity to develop treatments for diseases in which there are no therapies currently available and should proceed with the understanding that the technology will evolve and improve over time.</p>
<h2>Fireside Chat: Joseph Jimenez, CEO, Novartis</h2>
<p>Rounding out the fireside chat series, Joseph Jimenez, CEO of Novartis, sat down with Gregg Meyer, MD, Chief Clinical Officer at Partners Healthcare System to discuss:</p>
<ul>
<li>Changes that need to take place in the &#8220;healthcare system as a whole to a platform where all patients have access to therapies&#8221;</li>
<li>The company&#8217;s &#8220;IO strategy is to be strong with second generation approaches that target the tumor microenvironment&#8221; and the &#8220;shift away from a transactional approach to outcomes-based approach&#8221;</li>
<li>The four pillars: clinical value, patient value, health system value and societal value</li>
<li>The importance of intellectual property for driving innovation &#8211; &#8220;there are no generics without innovation&#8221;</li>
<li>The relatively low cost and continuing benefits, often extending over decades, of a drug once it comes off patent should be included in discussions of drug pricing</li>
</ul>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@lisamjarvis<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f601459fc4e9e21cc521a5eca4fe7232f151001776ea880ea">$NVS Jimenez: Just launched NVS Access&#8211;bringing 15 molecules to least dev countries, priced at $1/month/treatment #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@EmmaHokie<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f1969f9ebe7c3ff5a4d641648fbe4aadb36fba95aa0889f6e">Jimenez @Novartis: Intellectual property is the most important driver of innovation. There are no generics without #innovation. #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@PearlF<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f453cc07b3efc65425b8036be7fbfccb1cf7c9fa3bedfa8c6">Foundation Medicine CEO on reimbursement environment for Dx: Reimbursement is abysmal #wmif16</a></p>
<p>@AEDeconinck<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f8a50bffddb22509b52fba61f60ab67f60707a34444a38246">Why do FDA approved therapies get reimbursed but approval of test does not guarantee reimbursement? @MichaelPellini @FoundationATCG #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@bnikhil<br />
<a href="http://cl.s6.exct.net/?qs=b51a26116e379d1f0b22d17ab916585ee80b3f904a80a25f85a9fed1c50d84bb">3 challenges in cancer meds: Delivery, delivery, delivery #nanotechnology #WMIF16 Dr Farokhzad @BrighamWomens</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day Two Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/highlights-day-two-2016/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 16:06:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2386</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights of the Day Day Two of the World Medical Innovation Forum was brimming with fireside chats and panel discussions. The first session of the day highlighted the growing global cancer burden in which panelists from leading international companies and key government entities discussed the challenges to providing innovative technologies in diverse markets, as well <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-2389 size-full" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER" width="600" height="100" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER.jpg 600w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER-300x50.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER-220x37.jpg 220w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER-180x30.jpg 180w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-HEADER-140x23.jpg 140w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<h2>Highlights of the Day</h2>
<p>Day Two of the World Medical Innovation Forum was brimming with fireside chats and panel discussions. The first session of the day highlighted the growing global cancer burden in which panelists from leading international companies and key government entities discussed the challenges to providing innovative technologies in diverse markets, as well as potential strategies to overcome these obstacles.</p>
<p>In the second panel, experts provided an in-depth discussion on the promise of epigenetics for cancer research, describing the complex science behind the regulation of how genetic information is processed and the development of therapies that leverage these alterations to target cancer.</p>
<p>Two panels focused on the promise of immunotherapeutic strategies for the treatment of cancer, highlighting the recent burst in the field of immuno-oncology. A set of fireside chats provided insights into drug pricing, data sharing, collaboration, and patient-driven innovation.</p>
<p>The final plenary session, moderated by CNBC Biotech and Pharma Reporter Meg Tirrell, saw a panel of oncology investors discuss some of the most compelling topics in the industry today, including the most promising technologies, investment trends, comparison to other periods in cancer investing and, naturally, drug pricing.</p>
<p>The day concluded with four concurrent focus sessions, which provided discussion around radiation therapy, oncology devices, study design for personalized cancer medicine, and the unique challenges posed by increased cancer survivorship. For more in-depth highlights from some of the most interesting panels from Day Two, see below.</p>
<p>Notably, panelists demonstrated surprising candor when discussing their personal struggles with cancer, and seemed optimistic about the current trajectory of science, with the word &#8220;cure&#8221; being used more freely in the context of cancer and without reservations of this being a crazy notion, emphasizing the reality of working towards cures.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2390" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2" width="600" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2.jpg 600w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-300x100.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-220x73.jpg 220w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-180x60.jpg 180w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-2-140x47.jpg 140w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<h2>Global Cancer Markets</h2>
<p>As the global cancer burden is expected to increase from 14 million to 22 million cases by 2030, panelists from leading international companies and a key governmental entity, namely the famed National Institute for Health and Care Excellence at the UK NHS, discussed the future of cancer in a global market. Moderator Sheila Dharmarajan, Head of Business Development at Zelnick Media Capital, started out by emphasizing the term &#8220;tremendous&#8221; to describe not only the prolificacy of cancer, but also to describe the complexity of the market, breakthrough technology, and the dollars at stake in terms of both pricing and cost of innovation.</p>
<p>When posed with the question of whether pharmaceutical companies should fund diagnostics, panelists acknowledged that, due to the innate differences in business models, each company must decide their own path, but Bruno Strigini, President of Novartis Oncology, also noted the importance of considering the development of targeted therapies with companion diagnostics, which can be critical to providing the right products to the right patients.</p>
<p>Additionally, Newton Crenshaw, Vice President of North America Oncology at Eli Lilly and Company, stressed the importance of symbiosis between diagnostic and therapeutic companies, and indicated that reform is needed for regulatory bodies to accelerate diagnostics and provide access to patients. Following up on this point, Gillian Leng, MD, Deputy Chief Executive and Director of Health and Social Care at NICE, stated that this relationship could be most effective if regulatory bodies were allowed to evaluate the drug and diagnostic together.</p>
<p>As technology advances and we begin to consider cancer to be a chronic rather than terminal condition, Mr. Crenshaw also posed the question of how to best support patients beyond medicine, but noted that the cost burden of long-term treatment must be considered, as well.</p>
<h2>Immunotherapy: Checkpoint Activation, Cancer Vaccines, and Cell Based Therapies</h2>
<p>Day Two featured two panels on the promise of immunotherapy in cancer treatment in which panelists discussed various approaches to leveraging the human immune system to fight cancer, including checkpoint inhibition, anticancer vaccines, and CARTs.</p>
<p>In the first session, panelists were cautiously optimistic about immunotherapy as a tool for cancer treatment and agreed that this wave of enthusiasm is still in its early stages and we must proceed by paying particular attention to the determinants of tumor response and resistance. In this context, a recurring message was the importance of tissue biopsy and biomarker analysis before and during treatment, which will be critical to the understanding of what is happening to patients at a molecular level and, as Scott Rodig, MD, PhD, Associate Professor at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, mentioned, will be extremely important in the determination of rational drug combinations going forward.</p>
<p>Similarly, panelists also stressed that we should think carefully about how we are approaching combination therapy; rather than using a shotgun approach in which we try every drug combination, we should be deliberate in understanding the underlying mechanisms to predict optimal patient populations and avoid toxicity. More specifically, Thomas Daniel, MD, Chairman of Celgene Research, stated that we should be considering the patients for which combinations are medically valuable, along with a scientific grounding for why a specific combination makes sense, which is a more tractable and financially feasible option as compared to the shotgun approach.</p>
<p>David Reese, MD, Senior Vice President of Translational Sciences at Amgen, noted that a major challenge in the field at present is a need for the development of new surrogates for traditional response criteria; as patients live longer and overall survival becomes increasingly difficult to measure, some trial designs will essentially become intractable.</p>
<p>The second immunotherapy panel discussed what&#8217;s next for CAR T-cell therapy, with Usman (Oz) Azam, MD, Global Head of Cell and Gene Therapies Unit at Novartis, referring to the current technology to as &#8220;version 1.0.&#8221; Panelists discussed the promise of CART in hematological malignancies, but as Mark Frohlich, MD, Executive Vice President of Portfolio Strategy at Juno Therapeutics, pointed out, we must still determine the right targets for solid tumors.</p>
<p>When quizzed about the future of the technology, Dr. Azam also mentioned that gene therapy could be utilized to take CARTs to the next level, which Chuck Wilson, PhD, CEO of Unum Therapeutics, expanded upon by suggesting that the use of gene editing to target specific genes, create allogeneic T cells, or inhibit signaling pathways, could support the work of CARTs.</p>
<p>Dr. Wilson also reminded the audience that the reality is, as an autologous cell therapy, the logistics of taking cells from the patient, manufacturing cells, and returning them to the patient, will be inherently more costly than other therapies, but that scalability could bring this cost down. Additionally, as Marcela Maus, MD, PhD, Director of Cellular Immunotherapy at MGH, pointed out, the development of point-of-care methods or &#8220;off-the-shelf&#8221; T cells that could treat many patients with one lot are potentially less costly.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2391" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3.jpg" alt="Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3" width="600" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3.jpg 600w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3-300x100.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3-220x73.jpg 220w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3-180x60.jpg 180w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Partners-FORUM-2016-EMAIL-TEMPLATE-160426_1542-150-3-140x47.jpg 140w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<h2>Fireside Chat Roundup</h2>
<p>The first two days of the Forum were filled with fireside chats, which allowed for an intimate perspective on pricing, the importance of data sharing, academic and industry collaborations, current healthcare challenges, and much more.</p>
<p>Kicking off the first fireside chat of the Forum on Monday evening, Richard Gonzalez, CEO of AbbVie, sat down with Nancy Snyderman, MD, Medical Advisor, GE Healthymagination, to discuss:</p>
<ul>
<li>The acquisition of Pharmacyclics and the &#8220;blind dating process&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;Doubling down on R&amp;D&#8221; to bring a consistent stream of good medicines</li>
<li>Catering to patients by &#8220;bringing improvements for standard of care&#8221; that the healthcare system would reward</li>
<li>The most important model today of &#8220;partnering with academic and biotech&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Tuesday&#8217;s lineup of fireside chats started with Amgen&#8217;s CEO Robert Bradway and Bloomberg&#8217;s biotech reporter Caroline Chen on a variety of topics including:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need &#8220;to collaborate outside of your organization, especially with cancer&#8221;</li>
<li>The costly price tag that comes with innovation but &#8220;the need to focus on the benefit that it brings for society&#8221;</li>
<li>Project Data Sphere, an independent and not-for-profit initiative of the CEO Roundtable on Cancer&#8217;s Life Science Consortium (learn more here).</li>
<li>A call to society to invest more in cancer prevention</li>
</ul>
<p>With nine months left on the job, Andy Slavitt, Acting Administrator for the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS), spoke candidly with CNBC&#8217;s biotech and pharma reporter, Meg Tirrell on:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need for new payment models because governments don&#8217;t have &#8220;magic pots of money&#8221; and &#8220;we are still in the 1st and 2nd generation of pricing models&#8221;</li>
<li>Finding new ways to care for the &#8220;most difficult people with the lowest income and are disconnected from the healthcare system&#8221;</li>
<li>Pilot programs for cost containment and spurring innovation focused on &#8220;doubling down on primary care and prevention&#8221;</li>
<li>The qualifications for the next CMS administrator &#8211; &#8220;doesn&#8217;t need the job, doesn&#8217;t see it as a stepping stone, doesn&#8217;t need to make friends, and has struggled to find and provide care&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Praising the industry for its strides in finding important cures for cancer, Bristol-Myers Squibb CEO, Giovanni Caforio, MD, started off his chat with Meg Tirrell by highlighting three critical points to being a leading company in oncology: keeping the patient at the center, following the science and collaborations with industry and academia. Other topics included:</p>
<ul>
<li>The need for &#8220;different payment models and flexibility in the healthcare system&#8221;</li>
<li>The &#8220;beginning stages of understanding why patients don&#8217;t respond to immunotherapies&#8221;</li>
<li>The need to focus on biomarkers as &#8220;they are really important&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Rounding out today&#8217;s fireside chats, &#8220;patient scientist&#8221; Kathy Giusti, Founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation and Multiple Myeloma Research Consortium, spoke with Nancy Snyderman, MD, to discuss her journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Being a patient advocate, patient and business disruptor who has elevated attention and propelled advancements for multiple myeloma</li>
<li>The need for data sharing for research and cures</li>
<li>The &#8220;tough lifting&#8221; that comes with trying to stay on top of the cancer landscape</li>
<li>Partnership with Harvard Business School to &#8220;put together a business plan by which business and science could start disrupting&#8221; and &#8220;to bring the absolute best-in-class to ask the tough questions and to share and solve the problem&#8221;</li>
<li>How she made the decision to stop her own treatment</li>
</ul>
<h2>Live Coverage on CNBC</h2>
<p><a href="http://video.cnbc.com/gallery/?video=3000512872">View Meg Tirrell&#8217;s interview with Bristol-Myers Squibb CEO Giovanni Caforio</a></p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@PartnersWMIF<br />
.@ASlavitt @CMSGov says focusing on affordability won&#8217;t hurt innovation @megtirrell @CNBC #WMIF16</p>
<p>@Novartis<br />
It&#8217;s important to agree on what value-based outcomes means. It&#8217;s not just about cost but value to patients &amp; society -Bruno Strigini #WMIF16</p>
<p>‏@megtirrell<br />
Parachuting into Boston for the day for #WMIF16 &#8211; looking forward to some great panels &amp; our live intvw w $BMY CEO on @PowerLunch. Tune in!</p>
<p>@lisamjarvis<br />
$CELG&#8217;s Daniels: big challenge: anchoring IO combo regimens around testable biological hypotheses #WMIF16</p>
<p>‏@BWHResearch<br />
Dr. Sharpe: As we move forward, we need to understand the impact of dif therapies (targeted, radiation, chemo) on the immune system. #wmif16</p>
<p>@TomLynchMGH<br />
Two Things: Notable items from Tom Lynch, MD 4/26/2016: http://youtu.be/Pe85aTmrAu8?a via @YouTube</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day One Highlights</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/highlights-day-one/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 13:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2368</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[    Day One of the World Medical Innovation Forum began with a wave of young investigators highlighting promising developments in cancer research in a series of rapid-fire presentations. Recurring themes of the First Look session included the use of RNA in-situ hybridization (RNA-ISH) as a diagnostic tool, liquid biopsies for exosome analysis, and precision <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2369" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8366" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8366-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2371" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1393" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1393-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2370" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8378" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8378-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>Day One of the World Medical Innovation Forum began with a wave of young investigators highlighting promising developments in cancer research in a series of rapid-fire presentations. Recurring themes of the First Look session included the use of RNA in-situ hybridization (RNA-ISH) as a diagnostic tool, liquid biopsies for exosome analysis, and precision medicine approaches to patient care. Multiple presentations also highlighted the capabilities of the AMIGO suite at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, which uses intraoperative imaging to guide precise localization and analysis of patient tumors during surgery.</p>
<p>Attendees then had the chance to liaise with established Harvard Medical School faculty over lunch during the Discovery Café session, which paired interested Forum-goers with renowned leaders in their respective fields. Nearly 30 faculty members covered topics such as immunotherapy, diagnostics, therapy resistance, and the potential of CRISPR for research and therapeutics.</p>
<p>The Forum plenary opened with David Torchiana, MD, CEO and Anne Klibanski MD, Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, who welcomed an audience representing more than two dozen countries and introduced a program filled with high-caliber speakers and hot topics including immunotherapy, epigenetics, and bioinformatics. They emphasized the importance of collaboration to accomplish the goal of providing better care and support to cancer patients and their families and noted that the &#8220;engine of innovation is running better than ever&#8221; as we seek to push the boundaries of the many diseases collectively known as cancer.</p>
<p>After a series of thought-provoking sessions, Astellas Pharma announced the launch of the inaugural C3 Prize<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/11/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />. The day culminated with inspiring remarks from Greg Simon, Executive Director, The White House Moonshot Initiative and a fireside chat with Richard Gonzalez, CEO of AbbVie (stay tuned for more about the Forum&#8217;s fireside chats in tomorrow&#8217;s Day Two recap). For more in-depth highlights from some of the most interesting panels from Day One, see below.</p>
<h2>A War or Moonshot: Where Do We Stand?</h2>
<p>In the first panel of the day, Nancy Snyderman, MD, Medical Advisor at GE Healthymagination, sat down with Monica Bertagnolli, MD, Chief of the Division of Surgical Oncology at Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, and Daniel Haber, MD, PhD, Director of the MGH Cancer Center to discuss what&#8217;s to come in a new era of cancer research and care. The panelists were tasked with advising on whether cancer research and care over the next decade will be a war or a moonshot. Panelists agreed on both perspectives &#8211; a war because, from a patient perspective, it is a personal battle against disease and we must come together as an army to combat the disease and work effectively towards a cure, and a moonshot because progress in cancer happens with huge steps forward and reflects the combined efforts of a large group of people working toward a common goal, much like landing on the moon.</p>
<p>When asked about the funding landscape and future of academic research and development in oncology, Dr. Bertagnolli noted that, when money is tight, teamwork must be utilized, and support from patient organizations such as Stand Up To Cancer is profound. Dr. Haber also noted that we are at a magic time during which so much science is being translated, but that funds are also needed for basic research, with the rationale that, if all money goes to translational research and we do not value basic discovery, then there will be nothing to translate in the coming years.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2372" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1644" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1644-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2373" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1752" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1752-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2374" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A1799" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A1799-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<h2>Creating a Disruptive Cancer Pipeline and Winning Portfolio Strategy</h2>
<p>A focus of Day One included cancer pipeline and portfolio development, which began with a panel discussion of how to build and maintain a successful pipeline in a challenging environment. Panelists including Keith Flaherty, MD, Director of Clinical Research at the MGH Cancer Center, and Sean Harper, MD, Executive Vice President of Research and Development at Amgen, commenting on company culture and regulatory oversight of clinical trials.</p>
<p>Jay Bradner, MD, President of the Novartis Institutes for BioMedical Research, noted that we may not be able to visualize what a cure for cancer will look like at this time, as technologies are still emerging, but that we should beware of paradigms, as they can sometimes make you blind to the next breaking wave.</p>
<p>In a discussion of clinical trial participation, panelists stressed the need for improved navigation of study information for patients, which would in turn facilitate the interactions between these patients and their physicians and potentially improve recruitment. It was also noted that these patients should have access to expert opinion on the best trials for their disease; as George Demetri, MD, Director of the Center for Sarcoma and Bone Oncology at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute noted, it should not be so much easier to find the best Chinese restaurants on &#8220;Dr. Google&#8221; than it is to find the best clinical trial.</p>
<p>Panelists discussed the need for improved infrastructure that would hasten the timeline from ideas to clinical trials and noted that the FDA is responsive to novel approaches and is looking to industry and academia for advice. Dr. Demetri also noted that such an idea is on the table, with the proposed creation of an Oncology Center of Excellence at the FDA.</p>
<p>Overall, panelists indicated that the pharmaceutical industry is receptive to insight from academia, and that the field appears to be aligned in the early drug discovery mission. In a discussion of the interactions between small companies and big pharma, panelists noted that the small companies tend to be very innovative, but investments are risky. Sean Harper, MD, noted that pharma tends to be very open to bringing assets in to their pipeline, but would rather engage early on to ensure that it&#8217;s a good product, and that takes engineering.</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2377" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-300x200.jpg" alt="_H8A8454" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/H8A8454-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2375" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8432" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8432-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>  <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2376" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-300x200.jpg" alt="_MG_8445" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/MG_8445-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<h2>Curative Therapies: The Economics of Game-Changing Science</h2>
<p>As novel, potentially curative cancer therapies come to market, drug pricing has emerged as one of the hottest topics of discussion. Speakers shared their insights on the balance between affordability and continued innovation in the healthcare industry, which was emphasized by Betsy Nabel, MD, with the notion that we need to provide the &#8220;right treatment for the right patients at the right time&#8221; while making it affordable.</p>
<p>Speakers included Troy Brennan, MD, Executive Vice President and CMO of CVS Health, Paul Hudson, President of AstraZeneca US, Betsy Nabel, MD, President of Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, Gary Reedy, CEO of the American Cancer Society, and Peter Slavin, MD, President of Massachusetts General Hospital. The panel was moderated by Sue Siegel, CEO of GE Healthymagination.</p>
<p>In the session, panelists discussed how to measure the effectiveness of a treatment. Dr. Slavin noted that we are facing much more economic pressure in healthcare and that it is critical to eliminate care that doesn&#8217;t help our patients. Panelists suggested that the private sector, including commercial payers, academic medical centers, pharmaceutical industry, biotech, venture, and pharmacy should come together to determine the value framework, rather than leaving it to CMS.</p>
<p>Mr. Hudson noted an inherent risk associated with developing medicines, and that the demand for breakthroughs and targeting of smaller patient populations has never been higher, while Dr. Nabel reminded us that companies must also consider the costs associated with innovation, as well as the hidden cost for future development if innovation is left behind. Panelists suggested that pharmaceutical companies, insurance providers, and pharmacy benefit management companies should come together to share risk, as all parties would be incentivized if the risk is broadly distributed.</p>
<p>When asked about when cancer will become a chronic disease, a majority of the panel agreed that it would be within 10 years, while one panelist noted that, in some patient populations, the time is now.</p>
<h2>Notable Tweets</h2>
<p>@BrighamWomens<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/BrighamWomens/status/724685238237028355">&#8220;We want to ensure that our patients have access to clinical trials &amp; effective therapies.&#8221;- Dr. Betsy Nabel #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@MassGeneralNews<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/MassGeneralNews/status/724603589621108736">Are miniature devices the next tool in diagnosing + tracking #cancer? #MGH&#8217;s Hakho Lee discussing now #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@Novartis<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/Novartis/status/724691948683055104">We can&#8217;t be surprised we haven&#8217;t cured #cancer when we haven&#8217;t figured out how to respond to all its dominant causes -@jaybradner #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@bmsnews<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/bmsnews/status/724675347183230976">This is a historic time in cancer research. The opportunity is unprecedented. #ImmunoOncology research. #WMIF16.</a></p>
<p>@PartnersWMIF<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/PartnersWMIF/status/724656825027682304">.@JayBradner, Pres of @NovartisScience: &#8220;We have to beware of current paradigms&#8230; Can make us blind to next breaking wave.&#8221; #WMIF16</a></p>
<p>@CarolineYLChen<br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/CarolineYLChen/status/724747692841291776">$ABBV Gonzalez says his perspective as a cancer patient has made him go ahead w testing drugs in small populations that may not have big ROI</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kathy Giusti: A Profile in Innovation</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/kathy-giusti-profile-innovation/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 17:34:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2342</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What if choosing the very best treatment for any given cancer were as routine as choosing the right kind of antibiotic to treat a common infection? Kathy Giusti, founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation (MMRF), and a cancer patient herself, has made it her personal mission. She foresees the day when an individual’s medical <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What if choosing the very best treatment for any given cancer were as routine as choosing the right kind of antibiotic to treat a common infection?</p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/KG_Headshot.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/KG_Headshot.jpg" alt="Kathy Giusti" width="225" height="304" /></a>Kathy Giusti, founder of the Multiple Myeloma Research Foundation (MMRF), and a cancer patient herself, has made it her personal mission. She foresees the day when an individual’s medical care will be tailored in part based on each person’s genetic make-up and other unique characteristics of his or her disease.</p>
<p>“The days of a one-size fits all approach to cancer treatment are over. We can do better than that,” Giusti said.</p>
<p>The kind of precision oncology for which Giusti advocates has already proven lifesaving for some. Patients with many forms of cancer, for instance, undergo molecular testing as a standard part of their care, enabling physicians to select treatments based on this information.</p>
<p>“Armed with focused genetic and molecular information about their patient’s distinct disease, physicians can develop personalized treatment strategies designed for maximum effectiveness,” she said.</p>
<p>But making this routine, Giusti says, requires innovative research models that prize and data-sharing and collaboration to make unprecedented advancements, an approach for which the MMRF has become widely recognized. The MMRF, by working closely with partners in the biotech and pharmaceutical industries, academia, and the cancer community, injects speed and efficiency into the process of discovering and developing new drugs for the treatment of multiple myeloma.  Through this collective approach, myeloma patients now have 10 new treatments – 4 treatments FDA approved in 2015 alone &#8211; that have almost tripled their survival and given thousands of others living with this incurable disease a fighting chance.</p>
<p>Now, Giusti believes this same collaborative approach can be used to usher in a new era of precision medicine and its promise of a cure: the MMRF has pioneered an end-to-end solution specifically focused on precision medicine in oncology.</p>
<p>“We generate the data, we share and aggregate the data, we analyze the data, and draw insights from these data to develop optimal treatment strategies for patients,” she said.</p>
<p>At the core of the model is a robust data ecosystem, including the first multicenter multiple myeloma tissue bank. This endeavor allowed the MMRF, along with its best-in-class partners, to sequence the myeloma genome.  The MMRF also launched the expansive, comprehensive MMRF CoMMpass<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/11/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> (Relating Clinical Outcomes in Multiple Myeloma to Personal Assessment of Genetic Profile) study, which has performed whole genome sequencing on over 1,000 patients and generated the largest longitudinal genomic dataset in myeloma in the public domain. The MMRF then collaborated with partners like the Translational Genomics Research Institute (TGen) and the Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, to uncover deeper insights into the disease’s biology, such as BRAF, a target previously never linked to myeloma but for which treatments have already been approved for melanoma or are now in clinical trials.</p>
<p>“Studying a large number of people – deeply and over time – allowed us to ask and answer new questions that were never before possible,” Giusti explained.</p>
<p>Today, through CoMMpass study, the MMRF is tracking the progress of these same 1,000+ patients for at least 8 years, analyzing their genetic and clinical data to better understand how certain factors influence response to treatment and disease progression and to generate hypotheses for genomically informed clinical trials. Most importantly, these data are then openly and freely shared through a global learning network, so that brilliant minds from all corners of the scientific community—including experts at the big data analytics company GNS Healthcare—can collaboratively decipher patterns for further exploration. This network was built to democratize data, allowing researchers and clinicians worldwide to share and contribute to a growing knowledge base that can be used to generate hypotheses for clinical trials and rapidly explore new and potentially more effective ways of treating myeloma.</p>
<p>Any findings can be immediately advanced into the MMRF’s worldwide network of research institutions and cancer centers that are working collectively to test an arsenal of new drugs and combination therapies. More than 30 new therapies have been in clinical trials in the network, including genomically-informed treatments – that is, those that target specific alterations in an individual that give rise to cancer or promote its spread – and immunotherapies, like checkpoint inhibitors and immunostimulatory antibodies, which are drugs that make use of a patient’s own immune system to fight cancer.</p>
<p>The MMRF’s model also includes a community of patients, who Giusti says are “every bit a part of curing the disease as scientists”.</p>
<p>These patients are stepping up to share knowledge they have gained on their cancer journeys with fellow patients—including sequencing data, when available—so they can learn which type of myeloma they have and share their data to advance research.</p>
<p>“We consider these patients as partners in our search for better, more targeted treatments,” said Giusti.</p>
<p>“As these patients, eventually, have their genomes sequenced and learn which, if any, mutations they have, can connect with other patients, engage with researchers who specialize in that particular area of genomics, and sign up for clinical trials that might be appropriate for them,” said Giusti.</p>
<p>Giusti will share more details of the MMRF’s innovative end-to-end solution for precision medicine as she sits down on April 26<sup>th</sup> for a fireside chat with Dr. Nancy Snyderman to discuss “Patients Driving Innovation” at the 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum, hosted by Partners Healthcare in Boston.</p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together and its ability to improve patient lives.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Media at WMIF 2016: Engage with Us!</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/social-media-wmif-2016-engage-us/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2340</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[World Medical Innovation Forum 2016 is quickly approaching! Would you like to engage with us throughout the Forum and hear about all of the speakers, panels and presentations? If so, connect with us on Twitter and lookout for our blog posts. Our blog will provide daily roundups of the Forum and keep you informed about <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/">World Medical Innovation Forum 2016</a> is quickly approaching! Would you like to engage with us throughout the Forum and hear about all of the speakers, panels and presentations? If so, connect with us on Twitter and lookout for our <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/blog/">blog posts</a>.</p>
<p>Our <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/blog/">blog</a> will provide daily roundups of the Forum and keep you informed about the established leaders in cancer who will be attending and keynoting the event. Members of our team will also be live Tweeting from many of the panels and presentations.</p>
<p>You can use Twitter to not only keep up with the day’s panel discussions but also to engage in conversations with other participants and share insights into the innovations of cancer care that will be explored throughout the three-day event. Simply follow @PartnersWMIF and use #WMIF16 to join in on the conversation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2016 World Medical Innovation Forum to Feature Innovations Enhancing Patient Care from Prevention to the Needs of Long-Term Cancer Survivors</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/2016-world-medical-innovation-forum-feature-innovations-enhancing-patient-care-prevention-needs-long-term-cancer-survivors/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 18:40:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2336</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON&#8211;(BUSINESS WIRE)&#8211;Partners HealthCare today announced that the upcoming World Medical Innovation Forum™ will include a focus on patient care, ranging from discussions of the importance of cancer prevention and early detection and the innovations that are making it possible to the unique care requirements and new technology approaches to help survivors. The 2016 Forum, an <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON&#8211;(<a href="http://www.businesswire.com/" rel="nofollow">BUSINESS WIRE</a>)&#8211;Partners HealthCare today announced that the upcoming <a href="http://cts.businesswire.com/ct/CT?id=smartlink&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fmedforum17.wpengine.com%2F&amp;esheet=51318971&amp;newsitemid=20160413005469&amp;lan=en-US&amp;anchor=World+Medical+Innovation+Forum%E2%84%A2&amp;index=1&amp;md5=a27680c0a6877335e7f9d91c7424fec9" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">World Medical Innovation Forum<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/11/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a> will include a focus on patient care, ranging from discussions of the importance of cancer prevention and early detection and the innovations that are making it possible to the unique care requirements and new technology approaches to help survivors. The 2016 Forum, an annual collaboration and partnering event held in Boston on April 25-27, will focus on cancer. CEOs and senior company executives, top investors, policy experts, and Harvard scientists leading the charge in the fight against cancer will take the stage over the course of the three-day Forum for a series of sessions that will critically examine the innovations in and evolution of cancer care.</p>
<p>“Technological advances in diagnostics are beginning to make it possible to detect cancer at the earliest stages of the disease when treatment may be most effective,” said David Louis, MD, Pathologist-in-Chief, Massachusetts General Hospital and Benjamin Castleman Professor of Pathology, Harvard Medical School. “However, there have been many barriers to making these innovative tests widely available to patients, including the need for more research and development to ensure accuracy, better guidance to speed the regulatory process and new models to support their value and reimbursement. This Forum provides a space for us to learn about these exciting new diagnostic technologies and to collaborate on the scientific and economic challenges that preventative strategies and early cancer detection bring about.”</p>
<p>“Detecting cancer as early as possible in the developmental stage will help both patients and hospitals in terms of prognosis with possible cure or therapy regimens before the cancer has spread. It will also help avoid the economic burden typically associated with late-stage detection,” said Massimo Loda, MD, Senior Pathologist, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Principal Investigator, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, and Professor of Pathology, Harvard Medical School. “The technologies we are creating and pursuing are designed to detect and pursue cancer cells at the most vulnerable point in their development: the very beginning. The Forum will provide us with the opportunity to discuss those advances and learn of other new developments in a collaborative manner.”</p>
<p>The prevention of cancer and the development of new strategies to detect cancer precursors and early-stage malignancies when treatment may be most effective – clinically and financially — are critical research goals. The experts on the “<b>Early Detection and Prevention of Cancer</b>” panel will review powerful imaging modalities, single-cell analysis of the tumor microenvironment and next-generation cancer models. They will also discuss circulating tumor DNA testing to monitor response to treatment and emergence of cancer resistance—with the objective of early cancer diagnosis before symptoms appear. The panel will take place at <b>4:50 p.m. on Monday, April 25, 2016, in the Novartis Ballroom of The Westin Copley Hotel.</b></p>
<p>Panel participants include:</p>
<ul>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb">Moderator: <b>David Louis</b>, MD, Pathologist-in-Chief, MGH and Benjamin Castleman Professor of Pathology, Harvard Medical School</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Andy Chan</b>, MD, Program Director, Gastroenterology Training Program, MGH and Associate Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>William Hait</b>, MD, PhD, Global Head, Janssen Research &amp; Development</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Krishna Kumar</b>, CEO, Emerging Businesses, Philips</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Massimo Loda</b>, MD, Senior Pathologist, Principal Investigator, BWH, Dana-Farber and Professor, Department of Pathology, Harvard Medical School</li>
</ul>
<p>“The number of people diagnosed with cancer is continuing to grow at an astounding rate and while new treatment advances are enabling more and more of these patients to survive, there is an increasing need for innovative tools and resources to address the changing needs of patients, their families and the health care system,” said Claire Thom, Pharm D, Senior Vice President, Global Oncology Development, Astellas.</p>
<p>Extraordinary treatment advances have turned many cancers from apparent death sentences into manageable chronic illnesses with extraordinary consequences for the entire health care system. In the United States, there are approximately 14 million cancer survivors, up from just three million four decades earlier. Those survivors have unique care requirements, that will put enormous stress on the system and calling out for new technology solutions. A program, titled “<b>Surviving Cancer: New Realities, New Needs</b>,” will discuss those requirements and the technologies and approaches that can help monitor, guide, and connect patients. The panel will take place at <b>4:00 p.m. on Tuesday, April 26, 2016, in the Takeda Ballroom of The Westin Copley Hotel.</b></p>
<p>Panel participants include:</p>
<ul>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb">Moderator: <b>Tim Ferris</b>, MD, Senior Vice President of Population Health Management, Partners HealthCare</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Jani Ahonala</b>, CEO, Noona Healthcare</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Don Dizon</b>, MD, Clinical Co-Director, Gynecologic Oncology, Founder and Director, The Oncology Sexual Health Clinic, MGH and Associate Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Ann Partridge</b>, MD, Director, Adult Survivorship Program, Program for Young Women with Breast Cancer, Dana-Farber and Associate Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</li>
<li class="bwlistitemmargb"><b>Claire Thom</b>, Pharm D, Senior Vice President, Global Oncology Development, Astellas</li>
</ul>
<p>Sponsors of the Forum include Novartis, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Takeda Oncology, Amgen, Astellas, AstraZeneca, General Electric, Ipsen, MacDougall Biomedical Communications, McCall &amp; Almy, Mintz Levin, Ropes &amp; Gray, and Vertex. ST<i>A</i>T is the exclusive media partner of the Forum.</p>
<p><b>About the World Medical Innovation Forum</b><br />
The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of senior corporate, investor, and academic leaders. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together and its ability to improve patient lives.</p>
<p>For more information or to register, please go to <a href="http://cts.businesswire.com/ct/CT?id=smartlink&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.medforum17.wpengine.com&amp;esheet=51318971&amp;newsitemid=20160413005469&amp;lan=en-US&amp;anchor=www.medforum17.wpengine.com&amp;index=2&amp;md5=8031f35be853b120fe61ff34f3e6ef34" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">www.medforum17.wpengine.com</a>.</p>
<p><b>About Partners HealthCare</b><br />
Partners HealthCare is an integrated health system founded by Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital. In addition to its two academic medical centers, the Partners system includes community and specialty hospitals, a managed care organization, community health centers, a physician network, home health and long-term care services, and other health-related entities. Partners HealthCare is one of the nation’s leading biomedical research organizations and a principal teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School. Partners HealthCare is a non-profit organization.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/second-glimpse-first-look-next-wave-cancer-breakthroughs/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 18:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2335</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A Second Glimpse at First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs. For our last blog feature, we spoke with Alexander Lin, PhD, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School, and gave you a preview of his upcoming First Look presentation, <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>A Second Glimpse at First Look: </strong><strong>The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Mark-Cobbold.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Mark-Cobbold.jpg" alt="Dr. Mark Cobbold" width="210" height="294" /></a><strong><em>For </em></strong><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/firstlooknextwave/"><strong><em>our last blog feature</em></strong></a><strong><em>, we spoke with Alexander Lin, PhD, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School, and gave you a preview of his upcoming First Look presentation, “</em></strong><strong><em>Making the Virtual Biopsy a Reality: Advances in MR Spectroscopy of Cancer.” Our second sneak peek at the exciting discoveries to be featured in the First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs session comes from our conversation with </em></strong><a href="http://www.massgeneral.org/research/researchlab.aspx?id=1645"><strong><em>Mark Cobbold</em></strong></a><strong><em>, MRCP, PhD</em></strong><strong><em>, Associate Professor of Medicine at the Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH) Cancer Center and Harvard Medical School. Dr. Cobbold is a member of the MGH Center for Cancer Immunology and his research focuses on understanding how the healthy human-immune response is able to recognize and target cancerous cells and, when it fails, how it could be strengthened to recognize this threat. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Dr. Cobbold’s presentation will focus on “Tumor Antigens in Cancer and How to Manipulate Antigens to Stimulate Immunity.” You can catch him and a wide variety of creative minds presenting their most promising commercially related research during First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs, happening at the start of the Forum on Monday, April 25. </em></strong><strong><em>These rapid-fire presentations by early-career Harvard Medical School faculty will highlight compelling new discoveries and insights that will be the cancer care products of the future. </em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Tell us about yourself and why you have an interest in the World Forum:</strong></p>
<p>We moved my lab, the Cobbold Lab, about 9 months ago from Britain to the MGH Cancer Center and we’re currently looking into different immunotherapies for cancer. The research we’re conducting has lead me to conclude that most people have experienced some early form of cancer, but our immune response has protected us from these insults. We believe that in many cases it is when our immune response fails that we develop cancer. The solution we’ve developed is designed to strengthens the immune system to address the cancer in a very different but targeted way, instead of suppressing immunity like treatment with chemotherapy or radiotherapy.</p>
<p>Let me explain this a bit further. We have ionizing radiation going through our bodies every second of every day, and our cells accumulate a small number of genetic errors (mutations) regularly. Life is a process of genetic decay, and I passionately believe that as a long-lived animal living to about 80, which is our genetic life expectancy, we probably all develop cancerous cells thousands of times throughout our lifetime. Thankfully, there are multiple processes that prevent cancer from taking hold, some intrinsic to each cell through DNA repair and damage detection, and some extrinsic. Epidemiological data clearly shows for the first 50 years of our lives the incidence of cancer is very low suggesting that our bodies keep it at bay, and an immunological mechanism may play a dominant role in this. However, once you get past the age of 50, particularly once we get past 70, the incidence of cancer increases very rapidly. This correlates very strongly with the age at which our immunity starts to fail. Until recently, drug companies have been focused on finding ways to suppress immune responses to prevent the body from attacking itself (for patients with autoimmune disease). There is a huge arsenal of drugs available that can be prescribed to suppress immunity. In contrast there are very few drugs available that strengthen our immunity.  What we desperately need are new agents to stimulate and restore immunity and the pharmaceutical industry needs to spend the next 10-20 years developing such therapies.</p>
<p>My research is born out of real curiosity. We all have family members that have died from cancer, but I can’t say that’s what driven me to science. I’m driven really through intellectual curiosity and a desire to do something useful for society. In translating discoveries from the lab into the clinic, the process of innovation is critical for patients’ benefits, and the World Medical Innovation Forum seems to be particularly aligned and targeted towards that particular audience. I do a lot of work that could translate into the clinic, sort of bridging both sides of that pond, so the premise of the Forum is very close to my heart.</p>
<p><strong>Can you tell us a little about the Cobbold Lab and the work you’re currently doing with MGH?</strong></p>
<p>My lab at the moment is just getting off the ground, having been in the US for less than a year. One of the main projects we’re working on is how our immune system is able to identify the difference between healthy cells and cancer cells. In a sense, our immune systems are playing a continuous “Spot the Difference” picture game, where the immune system has got to look at the difference between the upper and lower picture panels, and sometimes the difference is not that easy to distinguish. To an immune cell (T-cell) a cancer cell could be a dividing healthy cell or an enemy, based on the coating around the cell. The question is how does the immune system spot the difference?</p>
<p>So part of my lab’s focus is taking a non-cancerous cell and a cancerous cell and characterizing the peptides on the surface of the cells. The immune system basically interrogates the peptide display on the cell surface and determines the difference between cells. We use a technique called Mass Spectrometry which is able to characterize peptides and spot the differences between cancerous and non-cancerous cells.</p>
<p>All cells are composed of proteins, and our DNA although critical to each cell, can be seen as just the instruction book that makes proteins. It is the proteins that function as the active parts of the cell; however, these parts can be decorated which controls their function. To use a baking analogy, the proteins can be thought of as cakes with the cell as the bakery. Using this analogy, the healthy cell bakery and the cancer cell bakery usually have the same cakes on sale.  However, the decorations on the cakes are very different. In the cancer cell bakery, the cherries (reflecting phosphate groups) haven’t been put on in the correct places, often showing extra cherries. A lot of research groups are looking for the “cake” vaccine. In my lab, we’re not interested in the actual the <em>types</em> of cakes. Instead, we are analyzing their differences by looking at what the cakes are decorated with, i.e. where the cherries lie.</p>
<p>The proteins in a cell are “decorated” with phosphate groups and sugar groups through a process called posttranslational modifications, which is like sprinkling cherries on top to maintain the baking analogy, and the number of cherries present changes multiple times during a cell’s lifetime. The difference between cancer and non-cancer cells is that the cherries, or phosphate groups, are put in different places and it turns out that these groups are retained when the proteins are chopped up and displayed on the surface of the cells. We believe this identifies a cell as either cancerous or not. Ultimately we can either look at the different cakes that exist, or we can examine how they’re decorated to determine a course of action for treatments and therapies.</p>
<p>Despite failing immunity <em>against</em> cancer, people with cancer still have strong immunity to viruses. Thus patients with cancer usually still have strong functioning immunity, it just isn’t focused on cancer. What we’re proposing is to decorate cancer cells to make them look like the viruses that people already have immunity to. In this way we are matching what is displayed on the tumors with what T-cells we have.</p>
<p>Arguably, we’ve got everything wrong right now with cancer therapies. From an immunology point of view, we are essentially strengthening the cancer by giving it new mutations through the use of radiation and chemotherapy, while suppressing the immune response at the same time. We are trying to poison the cancer and in the process end up poisoning everything else as well. Too often these treatments, unfortunately, only give patients a couple of extra months, and seldom curing the patient entirely. Currently, there is huge excitement in potentiating anti-cancer immunity and understanding how the immune system can detect and kill tumors, but also how tumors evade detection and control.</p>
<p><strong>What do you find is the most challenging aspect of your work? </strong></p>
<p>Well that’s a challenging question on its own! I’d have to say getting a hold of the right clinical material and data from patients is a challenge, and getting the right people and funding to continue pursuing one’s research is critical.</p>
<p><strong>Why did you come to the US?</strong></p>
<p>For those challenges really. Funding is a bit of a challenge everywhere. Competition is really high; I think there are too many researchers applying for the same pot of money. This keeps the quality of research high; but the price is huge sector inefficiency. I’m a bit of a paradox here, because I think it’s easier to get funding in Europe than in the U.S., and thus I’ve moved into a more challenging funding environment. But this is more than balanced by the huge opportunities here. Boston/Cambridge is one of the largest life sciences ecosystems in the world and thus a very efficient place to work, and that is a big draw on its own. There’s a lot of good stuff going on here, and from a life sciences’ perspective this place rocks.</p>
<p><strong>Will you be spending some time at the Forum after the First Look session?</strong></p>
<p>I’ll probably be staying around for a fair amount of it. I want these meetings to yield real actions that can produce real results for patients. This seems to be the ideal Forum to connect the right people together to really achieve something that hasn’t been done before. I’m excited to see what happens next!</p>
<p><em>The First Look session is shaping up to be an interesting dive into the most innovative technologies, treatments and therapies that are currently in the early stages of development.</em> <em>These brilliant investigators from Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute will each describe their work in highly organized 10-minute sessions. Access for this exclusive faculty engagement event is included in the World Forum registration.</em> <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/2016-world-medical-innovation-forum-registration-16705377233">Register Today!</a></p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together to improve patient lives. The 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum features the newest technologies to diagnose, treat and manage cancer. <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/">www.medforum17.wpengine.com</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/firstlooknextwave/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 15:33:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2301</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The World Medical Innovation Forum is excited to launch First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs. During this session, which opens the Forum on Monday, April 25, we will hear from a wide variety of creative minds on their most promising commercially related research, and what drives their passions every day. These rapid-fire presentations <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>The World Medical Innovation Forum is excited to launch First Look: The Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>During this session, which opens the Forum on Monday, April 25, we will hear from a wide variety of creative minds on their most promising commercially related research, and what drives their passions every day.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>These rapid-fire presentations by early-career Harvard Medical School faculty will highlight compelling new discoveries and insights that will be the cancer care products of the future. </em></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2296"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2296" src="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin.jpg" alt="Dr-Alex-Lin" width="200" height="208" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin.jpg 200w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin-96x100.jpg 96w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin-77x80.jpg 77w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Dr-Alex-Lin-60x62.jpg 60w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a><strong><em>One of the investigators presenting at the First Look session is <a href="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/speakers/alexander-lin-phd/">Alexander Lin, PhD</a>, Director of the Center for Clinical Spectroscopy at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Assistant Professor of Radiology at Harvard Medical School. Dr. Lin’s presentation will focus on “Making the Virtual Biopsy a Reality: Advances in MR Spectroscopy of Cancer.” His research interests include clinical applications of multinuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy in the brain, breast, and liver, and cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging. We recently had a chance to talk with Dr. Lin and hear more about the research he’s conducting, his goals moving forward, and what he finds most challenging in his work.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Please tell us about yourself and your interests in the World Forum:</strong><br />
I’ve been working in the field of magnetic spectroscopy for about 18 years now. It’s a very powerful research tool that affects many areas in neurological diseases, but it’s never really crossed over into clinical use. That’s one of my big goals, and that’s really why I came to the Brigham to try to translate this really powerful technology into the clinic.</p>
<p>Instead of getting pictures of the brain, or whatever body part that one typically does with an MRI machine, we measure the chemistry. The power of this technique is it allows us to really get a better understanding of what is going on pathophysiologically in the brain and other parts of the body. This technology is available on every MRI scanner and these chemicals that we can measure, the phrase we use is “Virtual Biopsy,” allow us to really get at what’s going within the tissue of the brain itself.</p>
<p>When we looked at ideas that could be commercialized, I really wanted to push something that I felt would be very clinically relevant and important. Take for example, a very specific marker for cancer – 2-hydroxyglutarate, a chemical that is produced only by a mutation that is found in about 70% of all brain tumors. The potential to use magnetic spectroscopy to measure this chemical is something that oncologists are really excited about. They have been ordering these [virtual biopsy] tests on patients, while also being a part of a number of clinical trials developing this technology further.</p>
<p>Connecting with potential collaborators who can help to advance the commercial application of magnetic spectroscopy is a part of my interest in the Forum. We’re already using this technology in clinics today, but one of the big barriers to widespread use and adoption has been that the software that we use to currently use analyze data has always been in the hands of people like myself, researchers. These research tools are not designed to be easy to use. It’s not designed to be friendly. It’s powerful and very accurate but difficult for clinicians to use within their workflow.</p>
<p><strong>Your recent Innovation Grant from BWH Department of Radiology and Innovation Hub focused on magnetic spectroscopy Tell us a little more about BrainSpec and what you’re hoping to accomplish:</strong><br />
I was very lucky to have a wonderful physicist working with me, Ben Rowland, who is also a brilliant programmer, and he, too, felt the ability to analyze data on this level was something that has been missing from the field. Together with Alex Zimmerman, from Harvard Business School, we put together BrainSpec, which is a web-based software platform to provide a brain cancer diagnosis within minutes without any surgical intervention and 100% specificity. This software is designed by radiologists for radiologists, and we have been working in conjunction with the Brigham Radiology Team as well as people even from MassArts and other local universities to really develop a software that would be intuitive and easy to use for people. Much in the way that Apple strives for simplicity in its products, you could almost call it the “Apple of spectroscopy” because it really tends towards being easy to use, therefore making it easier to implement in the clinic and to move this kind of technology forward.</p>
<p><strong>What do you find is the most challenging aspect of developing these kinds of technologies to facilitate early-detection?</strong><br />
For me, as a researcher, I’m not used to the business world. The requirements that are needed to take something from a prototype and turn it into a commercial product, such as FDA approval, are things I’m learning along the way. What’s been really valuable and fortunate is that we have the innovation staff at the Brigham and across Partners that have been incredibly helpful and supportive in trying to get this out there. The Brigham iHub really helped guide us through the process of what things are important and what are not in terms of developing a prototype. As a scientist you often get wrapped up in looking at the bigger picture and they really helped me stay on top of the important things, such as the user interface design. This platform will be fully automated and will allow us to get the results almost instantaneously, we’re talking maybe two or three minutes for it to spit back the information. Time and usability have been driving factors in BrainSpec’s development. As a researcher you just say, “Oh whatever, I’ll just code it” but there’s so much more to it and this has been very different and forced us to approach this platform in a very different way, which is of course new and exciting to me. It’s a newer way of looking at science than I had done before.</p>
<p>For the most part, this kind of technology has not been made available to the more general medical public, but we find it is currently thriving in academic settings. You have to find someone like myself who has experience in magnetic spectroscopy to translate the data as it stands right now. Making this more available on a clinical level is one of the goals of BrainSpec.</p>
<p><strong>Do you have plans to stay for the Forum after the First Look session?</strong><br />
Yes! I definitely want to see what else is happening and take part in this great networking opportunity. I’m entering this world of innovation so much more as of late, and there are interesting challenges I find myself facing as a faculty member in a hospital environment. It will be great to hear others discuss this issue, as well as other areas of development in oncology research.</p>
<hr />
<p>Dr. Lin’s research is just one of the exciting presentations featured in the First Look session. If identifying new high impact cancer technology is your passion—as an investor, company leader, donor, entrepreneur or investigator—this session is for you. These young stars from Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital and Dana-Farber Cancer Institute will each describe their work in highly organized 10-minute sessions. Access for this exclusive faculty engagement event is included in the World Forum registration. Register Today!</p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of more than 1,100 senior health care leaders hosted by Partners HealthCare in the heart of Boston. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together to improve patient lives. The 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum features the newest technologies to diagnose, treat and manage cancer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Global Impact of Cancer Breakthroughs to Be Featured at 2016 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/global-impact-cancer-breakthroughs-featured-2016-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 16:00:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2283</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON — March 23, 2016 — Partners HealthCare today announced that highlights at the upcoming World Medical Innovation ForumTM will include the global economics of cancer care. The 2016 Forum, an annual collaboration and partnering event held in Boston on April 25-27, will focus on cancer. CEOs and senior company executives, top investors, policy experts, <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="page" title="Page 1">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<p>BOSTON — March 23, 2016 — Partners HealthCare today announced that highlights at the upcoming World Medical Innovation ForumTM will include the global economics of cancer care. The 2016 Forum, an annual collaboration and partnering event held in Boston on April 25-27, will focus on cancer. CEOs and senior company executives, top investors, policy experts, and Harvard scientists leading the charge in the fight against cancer will take the stage over the course of the three-day Forum for a series of sessions that will critically examine the changing economic cancer-care landscape.</p>
<p>Novel, potentially curative cancer therapies are coming to market, with the promise of unprecedented patient benefits. While most key stakeholders have recognized the cost effectiveness of curative therapies, these therapies also present a challenge to payers in terms of the potential spike in patient volume and high cost as many of these innovative cancer therapies are being introduced. The “Curative Therapies: The Economics of Game Changing Science” panel will bring together top executives from the pharma, foundation, pharmacy, and provider sectors to explore cost effectiveness as part of regulatory approval. They will also examine the increasing emphasis on early detection, shifting incentives for oncologists, and how integrating billing codes, bundled payments, and management fees can help bring drug costs down. This panel will take place at 3:10 p.m. on Monday, April 25, 2016, in the Novartis Ballroom of The Westin Copley Hotel.</p>
<p>Panel participants include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Moderator: Sue Siegel, CEO, GE Ventures and Healthymagination</li>
<li>Troyan Brennan, MD, Executive Vice President and Chief Medical Officer, CVS</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="section">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<p>“The balance of affordability and the continuation of progress in the development of new drugs and therapies is an increasingly critical factor in cancer care and the way we treat cancer patients today,” said Gary Reedy, CEO, American Cancer Society. “This forum will examine some of the emerging issues that directly impact that balance including the cost of new innovations, procedures, diagnostics and medications, changes in reimbursement, and new models of care delivery.”</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<p>Health</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<ul>
<li>Paul Hudson, President, AstraZeneca US and Executive Vice President, AstraZeneca North America</li>
<li>Betsy Nabel, MD, President, BWH and Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</li>
<li>Gary Reedy, Chief Executive Officer, American Cancer Society</li>
<li>Peter Slavin, MD, President, MGH and Professor of Healthcare Policy, Harvard MedicalSchoolAccording to the American Cancer Society, cancer causes 1 in 7 deaths worldwide and is rapidly becoming a global epidemic. If rates don’t change, the World Health Organization predicts that the global cancer burden will increase from 14 million new cases and 8 million cancer-related deaths worldwide to 22 million cases and 13 million deaths by 2030.“The shift to treating cancer as a chronic disease and the multitude of new treatments and technologies available to health care providers are impacting the financial aspect of cancer treatment,” said Marc de Garidel, Chairman and CEO, Ipsen, the global specialty-driven pharmaceutical company. “The issue is treated differently from country to country and there are many lessons to be learned from the outcomes of each approach.”
<p>To kick off the program on Tuesday, expert panelists from leading international companies and key governmental entities, including the famed National Institute for Health Care Excellence, or NICE, in the United Kingdom, will discuss how approaches to deliver innovative technologies differ in various international markets, what the respective drivers are, and the requirements and challenges that must be met. The program, titled “Global Cancer Markets,” will focus on key strategies and trends in the international market and will begin at 8:15 a.m. on Tuesday, April 26, 2016, in the Novartis Ballroom of The Westin Copley Hotel.</p>
<p>Panel participants include:</p>
<ul>
<li> Moderator: Sheila Dharmarajan, Head of Business Development, Zelnick Media Capital</li>
<li>Newton Crenshaw, Vice President of North America Oncology, Eli Lilly and Company</li>
<li>Marc de Garidel, Chairman and CEO, Ipsen</li>
<li>Gillian Leng, MD, Deputy Chief Executive, Director of Health and Social Care,National Institute for Health and Care Excellence</li>
<li>James Robinson, President, Americas Operations, Astellas</li>
<li>Bruno Strigini, President, Novartis OncologySponsors of the Forum include Novartis, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Takeda Oncology, Amgen, Astellas, AstraZeneca, General Electric, Ipsen, MacDougall Biomedical Communications, McCall &amp; Almy, Mintz Levin, Ropes &amp; Gray, and Vertex. STAT is the exclusive media partner of the Forum.About the World Medical Innovation ForumThe World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of senior corporate, investor, and academic leaders. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<p>that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together and its ability to improve patient lives.</p>
<p>For more information or to register, please go to www.medforum17.wpengine.com.</p>
<p>About Partners HealthCare</p>
<p>Partners HealthCare is an integrated health system founded by Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital. In addition to its two academic medical centers, the Partners system includes community and specialty hospitals, a managed care organization, community health centers, a physician network, home health and long-term care services, and other health-related entities. Partners HealthCare is one of the nation’s leading biomedical research organizations and a principal teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School. Partners HealthCare is a non-profit organization.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Partners Event Gathers International Cancer Leaders</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/partners-event-gathers-international-cancer-leaders/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 19:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=2153</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON&#8211;(BUSINESS WIRE)&#8211;Partners HealthCare today announced the second annual World Medical Innovation Forum™, which will bring together more than 1,100 international cancer technology decision-makers from industry, investment, clinical and research communities, April 25-27, 2016 in Boston. Forum keynoters include the CEOs of Novartis, BMS, Amgen and Abbvie who will join more than 100 total speakers &#8212; <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON&#8211;(<a href="http://www.businesswire.com/" rel="nofollow">BUSINESS WIRE</a>)&#8211;Partners HealthCare today announced the second annual <a href="http://cts.businesswire.com/ct/CT?id=smartlink&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fmedforum17.wpengine.com%2F&amp;esheet=51290750&amp;newsitemid=20160302005224&amp;lan=en-US&amp;anchor=World+Medical+Innovation+Forum%E2%84%A2&amp;index=1&amp;md5=fc6287f453d6169ef1f5183a9fa6210f" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">World Medical Innovation Forum<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/11/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a>, which will bring together more than 1,100 international cancer technology decision-makers from industry, investment, clinical and research communities, April 25-27, 2016 in Boston.</p>
<p>Forum keynoters include the CEOs of Novartis, BMS, Amgen and Abbvie who will join more than 100 total speakers &#8212; all experts in new cancer technology from industry, the investment community and Harvard Medical School. World Forum attendees include senior executives, investors, entrepreneurs, clinicians and scientists. The focus of the Forum is new cancer technologies and the cooperative innovation among industry, academia, government and philanthropy required to make them happen.</p>
<div class="bw-release-story">
<p>“Cancer is a major cause of death worldwide. Developing new means of treating and diagnosing cancer requires an active collaboration between clinicians, scientists, companies and investors to identify and address patient needs,” said Daniel Haber, M.D., Ph.D., Professor of Medicine at Harvard Medical School and Director of the Cancer Center at Massachusetts General Hospital. “The outcomes of this cooperation will ultimately affect the lives of patients worldwide.”</p>
<p>Over the three days, the 2016 Forum will highlight emerging cancer innovations in immunotherapy, epigenetics, early diagnosis, combination therapies, as well as curative drugs, cancer markets, the role of patients in innovation, cancer as a chronic disease and investment strategies.</p>
<p>The Forum is co-chaired by Daniel Haber, M.D., Ph.D., and Monica Bertagnolli, M.D., Chief of the Division of Surgical Oncology at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Professor of Surgery at Harvard Medical School. Academic speakers include Harvard Medical School-appointed clinicians and investigators from Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital and the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute.</p>
<p>“The recent advances in the targeted treatment of cancer are extremely exciting and have set the stage for us to understand cancer biology as never before,” said Monica Bertagnolli, M.D. “While the progress in treating patients has been encouraging, cancer is a large and diverse group of diseases and it is continually evolving, making the need for innovation constant if we are to achieve our goals of prevention and cure. Pushing boundaries back requires collaboration across sectors.”</p>
<p>A highlight of the Forum is a showcase of the most promising cancer technology innovations from around the world &#8212; the 12 technologies with the potential to revolutionize cancer treatment and patient care over the next decade. The final selections, called “The Disruptive Dozen,” will be announced on the last day of the Forum. Another highlight will be rapid fire presentations by emerging cancer research stars. The “First Look: Next Wave of Cancer Breakthroughs” session will kick off the Forum at 8AM Monday April 25.</p>
<p>The World Medical Innovation Forum is organized by Partners HealthCare Innovation, a division of Partners HealthCare dedicated to advancing the commercial application of the unique capabilities of Partners’ academic medical centers. “The breadth of the topics that will be covered and the commitment to interdisciplinary engagement from international leaders across academia, finance, industry and public policy makes the Forum an unrivaled, must-attend event,” said Chris Coburn, Partners Vice President for Innovation and conference organizer.</p>
<p>Sponsors of the Forum include Novartis, Bristol-Meyers Squibb, Takeda, Amgen, Astellas, General Electric, Ipsen, AstraZeneca, MacDougall Biomedical Communications, Ropes and Gray, Mintz Levin, McCall and Almy, and Vertex.</p>
<p><b>About the World Medical Innovation Forum</b><br />
The World Medical Innovation Forum is a global gathering of senior corporate, investor and academic leaders. It was established to respond to the intensifying transformation of health care and its impact on innovation. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter the magnitude of that change, the center of health care needs to be a shared, fundamental commitment to collaborative innovation – industry and academia working together and its ability to improve patient lives.</p>
<p>For more information or to register, please go to <a href="http://cts.businesswire.com/ct/CT?id=smartlink&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.medforum17.wpengine.com&amp;esheet=51290750&amp;newsitemid=20160302005224&amp;lan=en-US&amp;anchor=www.medforum17.wpengine.com&amp;index=2&amp;md5=00364c8be6ad9045955125211cccc4a1" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">www.medforum17.wpengine.com</a>.</p>
<p><b>About Partners HealthCare</b><br />
Partners HealthCare is an integrated health system founded by Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital. In addition to its two academic medical centers, the Partners system includes community and specialty hospitals, a managed care organization, community health centers, a physician network, home health and long-term care services, and other health-related entities. Partners HealthCare is one of the nation’s leading biomedical research organizations and a principal teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School. Partners HealthCare is a non-profit organization.</p>
</div>
<div class="bw-release-contact">
<h2>Contacts</h2>
<p>Partners HealthCare<br />
<b>Partners Contact:</b><br />
Rich Copp, 617-278-1031<br />
<a href="mailto:rcopp@partners.org" target="_blank">rcopp@partners.org</a><br />
or<br />
<b>Media Contact:</b><br />
Kari Watson, 781-235-3060<br />
<a href="mailto:WMIF@macbiocom.com" target="_blank">WMIF@macbiocom.com</a></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can We Truly &#8220;Cure&#8221; Cancer?</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/can-we-truly-cure-cancer-2/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 20:41:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meaghan Doherty]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=1919</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Monica Bertagnolli, WMIF co-chair, chief of the Division of Surgical Oncology at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and chair of the Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology, a nationwide effort to test new therapies, speaks on Barack Obama&#8217;s aspirational plan in his final State of the Union to “cure cancer.” &#160; &#160;]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Monica Bertagnolli, WMIF co-chair, chief of the Division of Surgical Oncology at Brigham and Women’s Hospital and chair of the Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology, a nationwide effort to test new therapies, speaks on Barack Obama&#8217;s aspirational plan in his final State of the Union to “cure cancer.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Medical Innovation Forum Day 3 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/world-medical-innovation-forum-day-3-recap/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 22:21:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meaghan Doherty]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1514</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The final day of the inaugural Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum was a fittingly profound end to a thought-provoking meeting that featured leaders from business, research, and clinical practice discussing the most important and relevant topics of the day related to healthcare and brain disease. Reshaping Innovation Through Electronic Health The day began with <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The final day of the inaugural Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum was a fittingly profound end to a thought-provoking meeting that featured leaders from business, research, and clinical practice discussing the most important and relevant topics of the day related to healthcare and brain disease.</p>
<p><em><strong>Reshaping Innovation Through Electronic Health</strong></em></p>
<p>The day began with a conversation on the history and current implementation of electronic health records between Partners’ Chief Clinical Officer, Gregg Meyer, MD and Judy Faulkner, the founder and CEO of leading electronic medical records company, EPIC Systems. Faulkner shared the story behind and the philosophy with which grew the company 100% organically (without mergers or acquisitions) from a 2-employee shop in a basement in Madison, Wisconsin, to a healthcare software powerhouse with approximately $2 billion in annual revenues and over 6,000 employees. She explained that EPIC Systems designed the software from the very beginning with the patients and their records as the central focus and organizing principle.</p>
<p>EPIC systems supports all functions related to patient care, including registration, scheduling; clinical systems for doctors, nurses, lab technologists, pharmacists, radiologist and billing systems for insurers. With the comprehensive implementation of EPIC at Partners currently underway, Faulkner offered some suggestions about the implementation based on the experience of EPIC’s other major clients. She suggested that providers and administrators should take advantage of EPIC’s customization options, training offerings, user groups, and especially “MyChart,” the patient engagement platform, which is unusual among its peers because it has 10 times the number of patient users as it does provider users—illustrating that the patients are very engaged. Patients see it has a form of freedom, being able to fill out their own information in some cases, providing better care through self service. The applications vary from engagement through scheduling and payment, to video doctors’ “visits.”</p>
<p><em><strong>Gene Editing, Gene Therapy, and the Eye as a Gateway</strong> </em></p>
<p>During this panel discussion, leaders from industry and research discussed the progress and promises of developing effective gene therapies. Eric Pierce, MD, PhD, of Mass. Eye and Ear and Harvard Medical School, stated his sense that the community is truly “on the threshold of using all these technologies.” The panelists recalled some of the challenges and failures of the past 20 years, but highlighted some extraordinary advances, compelling drug candidates, and continued confidence in gene therapies becoming a more and more integral therapy for providers for both rare and eventually more common diseases (including HIV, sickle cell anemia, and thalassemia). Another panelist noted the great success of the CRISPR gene-editing platform, stating that scientists were overheard making statements rarely heard in genomics, such as “I tried it and it worked”. CRISPR is empowering scientists to make quick and inexpensive edits to stretch of DNA with a level of ease and efficiency not previously possible.</p>
<p><em><strong>MS Transformed: Harnessing Biology and Inflammation</strong></em></p>
<p>“MS Transformed: Harnessing Biology and Inflammation” brought together an expert panel across disciplines: Tim Coetzee, PhD, Chief Advocacy, Services, and Research Officer at the National Multiple Sclerosis Society, Alfred Sandrock, MD, PhD, Group Senior Vice President and Chief Medical Officer at Biogen, Howard Weiner, MD, Founder and Director of the Partners Multiple Sclerosis Center, and Michael Panzara, MD, Group Vice President and Therapeutic Area Head of Multiple Sclerosis and Neurology at Genzyme.</p>
<p>The panelists began the conversation by providing context into the multiple sclerosis (MS) landscape since the condition’s initial description 150 years ago. At the beginning of Weiner’s career in the 1970s, there was very little understanding of MS and no treatments or MRI scans available for diagnosis, treatment, and assessment of the disease. Today, MS is thought to be a success story within neurologic disease discovery as there are 12 FDA approved drugs on the market. The rapid rate of drug discovery and available MS therapies is largely due to a greater understanding of the mechanisms behind MS, the identification of testable targets, and measurable outcomes thanks to advances in biomarkers and MRI imaging.</p>
<p>These 12 drugs currently on the market are utilized as treatments of the relapsing-remitting type of MS and there are no known therapies specifically for secondary-progressive MS. This leaves behind a large population of MS patients in terms of therapeutic development and makes the current treatment choices far from perfect. Clinically, MS patients often go through a trial and error process to see which medications work best for them. Some patients can switch therapies for years before finding the right fit for them while brain damage continues to occur.</p>
<p>The emphasis on increased treatment options for individuals with MS leads into the question of what a cure will inevitably look like. Dr. Weiner mentions his three prong approach to a “cure”, which consists of: 1) rebuilding a damaged nervous system, possibly via stem cells and myelin repair, 2) controlling attacks through individualized therapies to stabilize the condition, and 3) eradicating MS through a preventative vaccine. Under this notion, the pioneering drug discovery process of the last two decades has led many MS patients to a “cure” as their disease remains stable without attacks.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, the panel enthusiastically agreed about the possibilities precision or individualized medicine will have for patients with MS and their physicians. The ability to prescribe the right drug to the right patient at the right time in the disease course will treat MS with greater efficacy and lead to an increased quality of life beyond the current trial and error system. Individualized therapies will undoubtedly involve continuous follow-up with patients that monitoring devices and big data will likely play a role in. It is not uncommon for current patients with MS to schedule clinical visits every 6 to 12 months, and a great deal can change in their symptoms and care during that time. Sandrock, MD describes a future that will utilize technology similar to a Google Watch for patients to measure their daily symptoms and regimens and scan for lesions and brain shrinkage without full-blown MRI imaging — all while contributing to pivotal clinical trials. Lastly, the panel mentioned an emphasis on drug discovery to help prevent and treat the secondary-progressive disease course. Upcoming therapies may also rely on the microbiome or human gut for answers addressing the role of the immune system in MS.<br />
As Panzara concluded, the questions that we will ask and developments we will make in MS research and care over the next 5 years are unpredictable and will surprise us.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Century of the Molecule Becomes the Century of the System </em></strong></p>
<p>Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital surgeon, bestselling author, and healthcare thought leader Atul Gawande, MD gave a moving and thought-provoking talk on healthcare quality and healthcare costs from the 19th century until today. He discussed the great reduction in inpatient mortality at MGH from the 1950s to the 1990s. Then, Gawande noted that the relative lack of improvement from approximately 1990 coincided with a dramatic increase in the cost per patient. He used this trend to frame a conversation about increasing cost and complexity without improvements in quality. He subsequently discussed the extraordinary reductions in patient mortality in surgery that had been achieved around the world at very little cost with the introduction of a coordinated systems approach and simple checklists used before and after surgery.</p>
<p>Using personal anecdotes and experiences, he discussed his more recent work around death and dying. He explained that since the 1980s, the trend has been that most Americans are dying in institutions and often while undergoing dramatic interventions. He explained that this flies in the face of many people&#8217;s preference &#8212; when asked &#8211; -to die at home and/or without such dramatic and often painful curative or “life-saving” measures. He closed by discussing the systems, planning, and checklist efforts he was helping to develop and implement to improve the experience of death for people and their families &#8212; often simply by making sure that providers, patients, and family members simply take time to discuss the patients&#8217; preferences and priorities around death and dying.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Builder’s Roundtable: Perspectives of Public/Private Payer Architects</em></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Partners SVP Tim Ferris, MD moderated a lively and insightful discussion about healthcare costs, payers, and economics with Aetna CEO Mark Bertolini and Affordable Care Act architect Peter Orszag, PhD, who is a Citigroup senior executive and former Director of the United States Office of Management and Budget (OMB) and Director of the United States Congressional Budget Office (CBO).</p>
<p>During this conversation, Bertolini shared his own dramatic personal and family healthcare history, as well as his perspective that healthcare in the United States was on a &#8220;burning platform&#8221; and that the Affordable Care Act created the impetus for conversations that needed to happen. Both agreed that the fee-for-service models are unsustainable and do not incentivize quality or cost control. They also agreed that the Affordable Care Act and related reforms were helping to move the country toward a new model that would be predicated on outcomes and include some mechanism to align incentives to encourage providers, consumers, and other market actors to contain escalating healthcare costs.</p>
<p>While emphasizing that extraordinary challenges remained, both shared some concrete reasons for hope. Bertolini shared that a targeted pilot program that Aetna had run to prevent hospitalizations among heart failure patients had reduced hospital visits by approximately 49%. Orszag shared his perspective that the recently announced 2.8% unadjusted Medicare cost increase was a positive sign that it is indeed possible to control healthcare costs and also that the Affordable Care Act may be having its intended effect.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day 3 Disruptive Dozen Overview</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/day-3-disruptive-dozen-overview/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 14:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meaghan Doherty]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1510</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A powerful summary of many of the innovations discussed at the Forum the past 3 days, the “Disruptive Dozen” is more than just a registry of buzz words; this list represents the optimistic current state of neuroscience and one to look back on in years to come to see the progress made. 12. DIAGNOSING AND <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A powerful summary of many of the innovations discussed at the Forum the past 3 days, the “Disruptive Dozen” is more than just a registry of buzz words; this list represents the optimistic current state of neuroscience and one to look back on in years to come to see the progress made.</p>
<p><strong>12. DIAGNOSING AND TREATING NEURODEGENERATIVE DISEASES THROUGH THE MICROBIOME</strong><br />
For the first time, the gut microbiome is now being examined as a therapeutic target. The body’s largest immune system holds many clues to neurological health. For example, a high-fat diet increases the risk for depression and other psychiatric disorders. Changes in the microbiome in the imbalance of certain bacteria could affect microglial cells in the brain.</p>
<p><strong>11. NEUROIMAGING FOR NEURODEGENERATIVE AND PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS</strong><br />
With more advanced, high-gradient 7 tesla MRI, the possibilities for imaging are plentiful. In Alzheimer’s disease (AD), comparisons are being made between the brains of symptomatic patients and non-symptomatic. Depression and anxiety – both neurocircuitry disorders – are being mapped with higher resolution and understanding.</p>
<p><strong>10. IMMUNE CHECKPOINT INHIBITORS FOR BRAIN CANCER</strong><br />
Checkpoint inhibitors could potentially stop the progression of brain cancer in certain subsets of patients. In advanced metastatic melanoma, where cancer reaches the brain, inhibitors produce better responses. Induced immunity is gearing the body for a stronger attack against the tumor.</p>
<p><strong>9. HEALING THE BRAIN WITH NEUROMODULATION</strong><br />
“Electricity for healing” is proving to be a viable treatment for improving working memory, making people more alert, and positively affecting people with neurocircuitry disorders such as tremors, addiction, PTSD, etc. There are 350,000 people in the United States with these “brain pacemakers.”</p>
<p><strong>8. MOLECULAR INTERVENTION WITH MINIMALLY INVASIVE TECHNOLOGY</strong><br />
The heterogeneity of tumors is affecting our approaches of targeting them. Because not every tumor is the same and not even the cells of one act the same all of the time, delivery devices with the capability of turning on or off different tumor expressions are key.</p>
<p><strong>7. NEW ASPECTS OF GENE THERAPY</strong><br />
More than 10,000 diseases are caused by a single gene defect. The explosion in gene therapy will be in editing techniques and “resilience” genes that can make diseases milder.</p>
<p><strong>6. THE PROMISE OF BRAIN BIOMARKERS</strong><br />
Finding biomarkers is the key to advancing drug development. For example, in AD, biomarkers found in cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) and on images of the brain appear years before symptoms present.</p>
<p><strong>5. THE PROMISE OF FOCUSED ULTRASOUND</strong><br />
The brain hides behind the skull and the blood-brain barrier. To be able to target deep tissue without radiation or incision means less time spent in the operating room and a quicker recovery for patients than current procedures allow. Less energy would be needed for the procedure, and reversible entry into the blood-brain barrier could mean safer, repeat procedures if necessary.</p>
<p><strong>4. RAPID INTERVENTION FOR PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS</strong><br />
In acute settings, suicidal ideation is an emergency. Symptoms of psychiatric disorders need faster intervention to keep patients and the people around them safe. Anti-depressants can take up to weeks to have an effect and may not produce an effect in some people. Techniques such as anesthetics, inhalants, and electrotherapy could soon be more widely deployed in emergency rooms.</p>
<p><strong>3. SMART BRAIN PROSTHETICS</strong><br />
Imagine what a “closed-loop thermostat” in the brain could do for many neurological diseases. They could restore quality of life to the physically impaired by stroke. These small devices would be implanted into the brain to stave off disease as it arises with no side effects.</p>
<p><strong>2. STEM CELL THERAPY TO REPAIR AND REPLENISH THE BRAIN</strong><br />
Regenerative medicine is recreating cells that are deficient, diseased, or missing. The use of stem cells and cell-based therapies is still controversial and presents moral and ethical issues as well as regulatory hurdles. However, it is undeniable that the brain is incredibly “plastic” and boasts an elegant biofeedback system. To use cells to correct a dysfunction requires great specificity.</p>
<p><strong>1. EARLY DIAGNOSIS AND TREATMENT FOR ALZHEIMER’S DISEASE</strong><br />
Fourty-four million people worldwide suffer from clinical AD, and many more go undiagnosed. It is a global health concern at the forefront of neuroscience. Speeding up drug discovery, tau protein immunotherapy, a-beta reduction, and robust imaging are just four of many tactics being used in the journey to a cure.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day Two &#8211; Focus Group Wrap Ups</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/day-two-focus-group-wrap-ups/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 17:20:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1498</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[National Security Through Neurodevelopment: County Initiatives to Meet CNS Challenges Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases threaten the United States and wide swaths of the globe. Alzheimer’s disease (AD), alone &#8212; where 120 million across the world may be affected by mid-century &#8212; may cost trillions of dollars. The economic burden on families and governments will be <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>National Security Through Neurodevelopment: County Initiatives to Meet CNS Challenges</strong><br />
Neurodegenerative and neuropsychiatric diseases threaten the United States and wide swaths of the globe. Alzheimer’s disease (AD), alone &#8212; where 120 million across the world may be affected by mid-century &#8212; may cost trillions of dollars. The economic burden on families and governments will be tremendous and could lead to a global economic crisis over the next generation.</p>
<p>The demographic trends are clear: In western society, we have added a third to our lifespan and have low birthrates. As a result, we face a tsunami as the populations across the globe age. Until recently, AD, was a fairly rare disease, with the risk being 1 in 8 at age 65, but rising sharply to 1 in 2 at age 85. AD will be a common occurrence more and more in the future, as it correlates well with age.</p>
<p>But governments across the world have been slow to recognize this. NIH funding for AD was approximately $600 million last year. By comparison, HIV/AIDS spending was over $3 billion. To invest now in basic research will save the estimated $1.2 trillion Americans will be spending per year to care for AD in only 20 years. David Cameron’s call for a global fight on AD during the 2013 meeting of the G8 is a start. The UK’s $100 million Dementia Discovery Fund is another effort to develop collaborations between the public, private and non-profit sectors.</p>
<p>To heighten the alarm and call to action, we ought to stop looking at this just as a disease process, but rather as an economic crisis. WHO has issued a report on the coming pandemic. But where are reports from the World Bank or IMF? We should re-think spending on health and medical research not as a cost but as an investment &#8212; just as we did on a global scale with HIV/AIDS.</p>
<p>Due to stigma, there’s no public voice for mental illness as there is for other diseases. And for mental illness, the funding situation is even more critical. NIH spends far less on mental illness than other neurological conditions. Pharma is still investing in neuro, but it is getting out of R&amp;D and drug discovery for psychiatry. This will obviously reduce the number of therapies in clinical trials and will drastically reduce the pipeline of young scientists entering the field.</p>
<p>Perhaps a paradigm shift in our thinking will help: AD is not as a disease of 80-year olds; it is a disease in its early stages of people in their 40s and 50s. Collaboration and leadership are needed from the political, corporate and NGO sectors to capitalize on this realization. After all, our collective cognitive health will equal our economic wealth.</p>
<p><strong>Technology, Pathology, Radiology: Changing the Game through Neurodiagnostics </strong><br />
The promise in imaging lies in being able to detect disease through multiple modalities and thus, diagnose sooner and more accurately. In the past, neurological diseases were studied post-mortem, and we depended on lesions to show function and structural correlation. The shift has moved from first a gross level, then a cellular level, and now a molecular level – finding out which genes and proteins are altered to cause inflammation and tissue damage. Becoming more “micro” and using data analytics will be continuing trends. Today’s imagers and pathologists are excited about possibilities in wearable MR, and radioomics. The recent changes in WHO classification of brain tumors to add molecular properties shows the global shift of diagnostics towards a more personalized approach. Our techniques are getting smaller and data is getting bigger – a promising combination.</p>
<p><strong>Autism and Neurodevelopment: Are Therapies Possible Today?</strong><br />
This session, moderated by Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author, and Director of the Project on Public Narrative at Harvard University, Ron Suskind, explained that, 20 years ago, his own son was diagnosed with autism, at a time when not much was known of this “Rainman” affliction. The diagnosis of autism has exponentially increased and is now largely a public health issue.</p>
<p>The panel focused on the hurdles the speakers collectively face studying autism. The majority, about 25% of severe autism disorders, does not have an obvious genetic defect. In fact, there may not be a relationship between what is seen clinically and genetically in autism. It was said that in autism, there are no treatments; therefore small improvements can be revolutionary. Measurements of outcomes in drug developments in autism research are also quite complex. Parent warriors are often scientists who were touched by autism in a personal way, as is directly seen on this panel. Social media has made broad-reaching clinical trials possible, connecting with other parent warriors from far and afield. Crowd source funding is also utilized.</p>
<p>A collective goal amongst the panelists is to better understand the molecular defect(s) of autism, and to determine a way to objectively measure outcomes of experimental treatment. One panelist offers the possibility to discover treatable idiopathic subtypes of autism. Perhaps inflammation plays a causal role in some subtypes of autism that can be targeted with effective therapies. Collectively grappling with the impressive and challenging future of autism research, it does not seem that any of these panelists are capable of limiting themselves in their pursuit to define, treat and end this disease. In the end, the moderator, Ron Suskind, Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author and Director of the Project on Public Narrative at Harvard University, also rallied for the societal inclusion of those already autism-afflicted, highlighting the strengths or passions of differently-abled people, while seeking creative adaptations and treatments to enhance their quality of life.</p>
<p><strong>Pyschiatric Targets: Finally New Mechanisms</strong><br />
Today, most of us know – either as family members, friends or work associates – people who suffer from some form of psychiatric disease. Yet, the delivery of care and the corresponding investment in research, infrastructure, and medical support suffer from a disproportionate lack of resources, compared to other targeted health programs such as cancer. As was noted in the earlier session on neurostimulation, venture capital investment for psychiatric diseases is less than 10% of the cancer investment. Maurizio Fava, M.D., Executive Vice Chair, MGH Psychiatry and Slater Family Professor of Psychiatry at Harvard Medical School, added that the drug therapies available today (mostly monoamines) have been available for years, and very few new drugs have made it to Phase 3 trials. Other participants contributed their analyses about why the industry has not championed new therapies.</p>
<p>Deborah Dunsire, M.D., as CEO of FORUM Pharmaceuticals, stated “Show me the target.” Her assessment of the industry is that the therapies and outcomes lack the tools to successfully predict the risk of the investment. Fava commented that the placebo effect resulted in a number of Phase 3 trials being abandoned.<br />
One theme was the need for better biological markers that can be used in providing more accurate and actionable diagnoses. David Silbersweig, Chairman, Psychiatry at BWH and Stanley Cobb Professor of Psychiatry at Harvard Medical School, in his opening comments, referred to the difficulty of working with patients where many of the symptoms are self-reported. He also pointed out how recent research has identified the high level of interaction between the executive functions and the limbic system – which makes some of the traditional categories less useful. Instead, he emphasized that new methods have explored the role of the environment along with current therapies. Part of this discussion was also the need for better metrics for outcomes.</p>
<p>Another theme was the emerging use of CBT (cognitive behavioral therapies). Corey McCann, M.D., Ph.D., Founder and CEO, Pear Therapeutics, discussed the approach his company has taken in merging software-based CBT technology with various drug therapies. The panel discussed the application of CBT to post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and the underlying mechanisms that deal with fear circuitry. CBT – using contemporary game technology – allows the patient to work through his or her fear experience so that the narrative can be selectively disassociated from the emotional response. PTSD has gained a lot of recent attention in the industry, partly because of the need to treat the veteran population. McCann stated that studies have shown that CBT plus an antidepressant have treated depression better than either one alone. It also has the benefit of working with several existing drugs, and it can be deployed for new indications without some of the overhead currently associated with FDA approval of new drugs.<br />
Other topics covered included addiction, active and passive monitoring using cell phone technology, and imaging. The panel was generally upbeat about the future.</p>
<p><strong>Sleep and Consciousness: Clinical Need Versus Safety</strong><br />
Sleep serves as the bedrock of good health. And poor sleep, either in duration, quality or continuity, may have significant negative implications for overall health.</p>
<p>While we sleep, parts of our brain are quite active. Deep, slow-wave sleep at the beginning of a sleep cycle helps to consolidate memory, while REM stage sleep that occurs much later in the sleep cycle helps us integrate what we have learned. REM sleep assists with the development of insight and understanding. And when we are asleep, the brain’s own drainage system removes harmful metabolites like amyloid beta.</p>
<p>A number of factors get in the way of sleep. Many of us are over-caffeinated and spend too much time in front of TV and other device screens. The light emitted by these devices interferes with the normal role of melatonin and delays the onset of sleep. Millions of others, many unaware, suffer from interrupted breathing during sleep – sleep apnea. Still others face chronic disorders of insomnia and narcolepsy. Chronic pain and psychiatric illnesses can also disrupt sleep.</p>
<p>Research is needed to identify biomarkers so that personalized therapies can be developed. Intensive effort and significant resources will be needed to see if it is possible to come up with a blood test to indicate who among us is at greater risk for a given sleep disorder. It was once thought that all sleep apnea, for example, was the same. Research has shown there to be a number of subtypes. Continued work to indentify subtypes will help develop more effective therapies.</p>
<p>Many of the wearable computing devices like Fitbit and sleep monitors are generating great interest. As more and more individuals are collecting data, including on sleep habits, patterns are emerging. This data may also be used for diagnostic and treatment purposes. However, these devices are early prototypes and as such, can produce erroneous data or even be “tricked” into producing false results. As they become more sophisticated, they may be able to offer more insight into sleep and other health indicators.</p>
<p>Exciting new areas to be explored include the genetics of sleep pathology. This coincides with the groundswell of interest in personalized medicine.</p>
<p><strong>Parkinson’s: Finally Crossing the Therapeutic Threshold</strong><br />
The first part of this panel focused on the need for better biological markers which would result in enhanced diagnostic capability, and the second part dived into current therapies for Parkinson’s disease. Michael Schwarzchild, M.D. Ph.D., Chair, Parkinson Study Group Executive Committee at MassGeneral Institute for Neurodegenerative Disease, and Professor Neurology, Harvard Medical School, opened the session by providing an overview of what Parkinson’s is and its prevalence in the population (second most common disease behind Alzheimer’s). He also reviewed some of the recent findings, particularly in the emergence of some of the genetic clues and their complex interactions with environmental factors. New insights have been gained on the progress of the disease and early diagnosis. He stressed that the most typical symptom of Parkinson’s – tremors and other motor disorders – is not necessarily the first manifestation of the disease (for example, sleep disorders, depression, etc.) As he remarked later in the session, there is still no unifying hypothesis for Parkinson’s.<br />
The difficulty in identifying biomarkers was complicated by the effect of patients already in treatment. Some studies have taken 10 years and have been very costly. Clemens Scherzer, M.D., Director, Neurogenomics Lab and Parkinson Personalized Medicine Program, Brigham and Women’s Hospital/Massachusetts General Hospital, and Associate Professor of Neurology, Harvard Medical School, described the collaborative approach his team has taken at Harvard and the positive results they have achieved. Results are now measured in weeks rather than years. Todd Sherer, CEO of the Michael J. Fox Foundation, also championed collaborative research and described some successful programs they have run. So far, the strongest markers have been genetic.</p>
<p>Current therapies seem to be centered on the continued use of dopamine-based strategies. Scherzer noted that of 35 recent trials, only a handful include disease-modifying drugs. The improvements are more focused on better delivery mechanisms, so that a patient can gain relief in a matter of minutes rather than in 30 to 40 minutes (based on inhalationm versus oral intake). More work is also being done on integrating non-motor symptoms into the treatment portfolio.</p>
<p><strong>New Leaders at the Table: Filling the Gap Through Philanthropy</strong><br />
Henry McCance, dynamic speaker and Co-Founder of Cure Alzheimer’s Fund eloquently defined this nonprofit organization, founded in 2004, by several families who were frustrated by the slow pace of research. This fund is a new venture-based entity created to speed research and exclusively focus on finding a cure, leveraging successful returns that de-risk research and thus become more attractive to public funding sources.<br />
Meryl Comer, President of the Geoffrey Beene Foundation’s Alzheimer’s Initiative, spoke of her role as long-term caregiver of her afflicted husband and her realization that she needed to turn the suffering into purpose. Comer spoke of actively changing the direction and pace of medical research, by mining public databases, or “big data,” and not focusing on reinventing the wheel, as well as utilizing collaborative technologies to help foster data collection and analysis. The Initiative has generated more than $4.8 million so far, in support of awareness programs and early diagnostic and treatment research.</p>
<p>Nancy Frates, mother of Pete Frates, described how their family enveloped themselves in philanthropic relationships that banded together to amplify funding for ALS research. A fellow ALS sufferer came across the Ice Bucket Challenge and brought it to Pete’s attention, and the Frates family quickly and efficiently used social media to use the Challenge to spread the word, as well as to raise the funds to be proactive and accelerate ALS research.<br />
CEO of Forma Therapeutics, Steven Tregay, spoke of how Forma is helping to transform the drug discovery process through collaborations in pharma.</p>
<p>Jeff Walker, Vice Chair, United Nations Envoy Office of Health and Finance and Malaria, shared that he just lost his father t Alzheimer’s last Friday. He spoke of pointing out to investors that their investment “return” is invaluable.<br />
Bill Sahlman, Senior Associate Dean of Harvard Business School, brilliantly defines the biggest “data dumps: on everyone’s hips, the cell phone. The importance of gathering information on a big scale is very important, and cell phones are ideally placed for this purpose. He does not feel that privacy concerns should get in the way of utilizing these ubiquitous tools for research purposes.</p>
<p>The takeaway message of this panel was that in an age where we are living longer lives, it may be that it’s not if you get Alzheimer’s, it’s when, and we should all be active investors in its prevention, treatment and cure.</p>
<p>Posted by Jim Coburn, Christine Dyer-Ward, John Hannigan and Fares Nigim</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Forum – Day 2 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/world-forum-day-2-recap/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 14:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1497</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second day of the World Medical Innovation Forum continued to build momentum on the Forum’s mission — providing a venue for imperative conversation among academic, private, government and patient/consumer communities. The agenda set forth today brought together stakeholders across disciplines — patients living with neurologic conditions and leaders in academic medical research, private biotechnology, <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The second day of the World Medical Innovation Forum continued to build momentum on the Forum’s mission — providing a venue for imperative conversation among academic, private, government and patient/consumer communities. The agenda set forth today brought together stakeholders across disciplines — patients living with neurologic conditions and leaders in academic medical research, private biotechnology, and government. The one-on-one panel format paved the way for candid insight into where the field of neurosciences has been for the past 30 years and where it is heading, at an accelerated pace, via collaboration and conversation.</p>
<p><strong><em>Clinical Demonstrations </em></strong><br />
The first session started early and strong with demonstrations from two of neuroscience medicine’s most promising tools, the AMIGO Suite and NeuroSwitch. The AMIGO Suite is a $20 million multi-modality operating room pioneered at the Brigham and Women’s Hospital (BWH). This robust theater is intraoperative imaging at its best, the concept first conceived at BWH in the 1990s. It is equipped with CT, MR, fluoroscopy, among others, and the world’s only intraoperative PET/CT scan. Suites featuring intraoperative imaging are now adopted widely across the United States and the world.</p>
<p>The goal of these suites is to make surgery safer by assisting surgeons in distinguishing normal versus cancerous tissue. This guidance, along with superior imaging technique, allows neurosurgeons to contour a mass with unprecedented approximation and aids in real-time clinical decision-making. Suites like AMIGO are multi-specialty and can be applied to systems other than the brain and therefore, engage a wide array of the clinical community. Transforming a maximally invasive procedure into a minimally invasive one and being able to operate on a formerly inoperable patient are the underlying incentives for using such suites.</p>
<p>What are brain surgeons currently excited about? More precision for better outcomes. Metabolite-guided surgery through mass spectroscopy, delivery of drugs into the central nervous system (CNS), and laser hyperthermia to destroy tumors. The AMIGO Suite is able to use any type of instrument, metallic or not. A versatile OR is a vehicle of the future, and the world’s eyes are on BWH and the AMIGO suite.</p>
<p>NeuroSwitch is unlike the typical communication aids available on the market. It gets past the physical interface (buttons, keyboards, clickers) and uses movements and EEG data to control a computer device. Patients with locked-in syndrome (LIS), most commonly found in ALS, are able to use NeuroSwitch to regain control of their self-expression. The market size is growing – 35,000 patients suffer from ALS in the United States, with 5,000 new diagnoses annually. The ability for patients to communicate with not only their loved ones, but also with the world online is paramount for them. Patients who use NeuroSwitch gave live demonstrations, raving about NeuroSwitch and how it allows them to keep their passions, like book blogging or 3D printing, alive. When motor control diminishes, sophisticated, hands-free communication aids are mandatory. With features like the ones NeuroSwitch boasts, patients are able to stay connected with their families and communities.</p>
<p><strong><em>Patient One-on-One</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1499" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-300x200.jpg" alt="Ann Romney" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM-93x62.jpg 93w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6858-SM.jpg 1368w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><br />
</em></strong>Serving as the official launch of the Ann Romney Center for Neurological Diseases at BWH, Ann Romney spoke to Forum attendees about her personal journey with multiple sclerosis (MS). She was diagnosed in 1998 and expressed how fortunate she was to have received early and aggressive treatment at BWH. She is now currently in remission and on no medication, a state of health not realized by many other patients who suffer from neurologic disease worldwide. She maintains her stellar health by rigorous fitness regimens and diets, as well as a spiritual and mental wellbeing that is fostered by her passion for horseback riding. She credits both physicians at BWH and her dedicated supporters who were there for her on the campaign trail during her husband’s past presidential bid.</p>
<p>The Ann Romney Center for Neurological Diseases will support research and innovation in MS, Alzheimer’s disease (AD), Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS), Parkinson’s Disease, and brain tumors. She hopes that this horizontal model will instigate interdisciplinary collaboration. The overlap in many neurological illnesses calls for a different approach and to break down the silos of disease cures and therapy research and development efforts. There is power in numbers, and she encourages all who are affected by neurological disease to join her new social media campaign by using the hash tag, #50MillionFaces, on Twitter.</p>
<p><strong><em>The Alzheimer’s Phoenix: New Technologies, New Economics<br />
</em></strong>This panel of esteemed and diverse AD experts shed light on the current theories of disease causes and what to expect on the journey to a cure. All were very optimistic and agreed that we are close to disease-modifying therapies that could be marketable as soon as five years from now. It has taken decades to validate the two-tiered pathology of AD in amyloid-beta (a-beta) and tau protein aggregation. The future lies in combining these theories into parallel therapies to enhance clinical effect. Base inhibitors have been found to be very promising and are currently the most competitive targets in the industry. When given to compliant patients for a year, a-beta was eliminated almost entirely. This is the epitome of reverse translational medicine – aiding the immune system in recognizing these destructive protein aggregates.</p>
<p>As the underlying causes of AD become clearer, early and personalized treatment for patients has become more realistic. In the autopsies of people who died of suspected AD, almost 1/3 of their brains were seen to be damaged. According to the speakers, clinicians must realize that AD is malicious organ failure that starts decades before being symptomatic, if at all. The heterogeneity of the population with AD in years to come will help evolve treatment. It will not be long before we are treating AD patients based on their own specific symptoms and biology. Today’s speakers advised that clinicians need to start utilizing a risk-assessment profile to plan beyond the long prodromal period and optimistically provide a risk “score” as early as age 40.</p>
<p>Where are there room for improvements in AD care? There has to be greater coordination among payers to coordinate cost-effectiveness. The late-stage AD patient requires 24-hour care, multiple caregivers, and an extensive clinical team. The advances to come will hopefully allow patients to maintain more independence and a greater quality of life and have care at an as-needed basis. Investigators need to focus their efforts on finding the right genes and biomarkers for drug development. Non-pharmacological interventions should be integrated into care and be viewed just as importantly as drugs. Poor diet and scarce exercise cannot be compensated for by better drugs. The stratification of AD patients as at-risk, non-symptomatic, early-stage, or late-stage, require individualized care and treatment.</p>
<p><strong><em>Regeneration, Cell Therapy, and Neurocare: Products? Delivery?<br />
</em></strong>Regenerative medicine is recreating cells that are deficient, diseased, or missing. The use of stem cells and cell-based therapies is still controversial and presents moral and ethical issues as well as regulatory hurdles. However, it is undeniable that the brain is incredibly “plastic” and boasts an elegant biofeedback system. To use cells to correct a dysfunction requires great specificity. Cell-based therapies have the potential to be applied across disciplines in spinal cord injury, diabetes, and blood dyscrasias. In spinal cord injury, “cross-correction” can produce enough of a missing enzyme in defective neurons for them to remain viable. Diabetics can be unleashed from a life support of administered insulin with the replacement of defunct beta cells in the pancreas. In inherited disorders like sickle cell anemia and thalassemia, gene editing can reprogram cells to be embryonic, enabling patients to essentially “get their cells back.” The targeted diseases for stem cell research are typically ones that have no treatments; any work in this field, therefore, will address a large unmet need.</p>
<p>There are two types of cells used in regenerative therapies: embryonic, or immature cells derived from embryos, and “adult” cells that come from a formed organ. Embryonic cells can potentially produce any cell type in the body – providing a wealth of possibility yet also result in the chance of tumorgenecity, or the primitive cell developing into a tumor. There are ways to address this by pre-determining cells or turning on “suicide genes” to kill the cell once it starts to express tumorgenecity. This controversial technique has the potential to save tens of thousands of lives but will not be adapted into practice if headway cannot be made by industry and academia, together, in addressing the treatment risks.</p>
<p><strong><em>CEO One-on-One Sessions</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1500" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-300x200.jpg" alt="Robert Bradway" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7115-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><br />
</em></strong>The personal one-on-one accounts continued throughout the day with candid conversations between leaders in the private biotechnology industry and government. Robert Bradway, CEO of Amgen, and George Scangos, Ph.D., CEO of Biogen, reflected on the challenges and successes to date in identifying and producing novel therapies for devastating neurologic diseases.</p>
<p>Bradway said that Amgen is a leader in drug development across various diseases like chronic kidney disease, cardiovascular disease, inflammation, and the company is increasingly interested in getting more involved in the neurosciences. Some drugs in their current pipeline are early-stage treatments for schizophrenia, AD, and chronic pain. Amgen is currently active in genetics, and Bradway sees a sustaining trend in favoring genetics for informing drug development.</p>
<p>Bradway discussed Amgen’s acquisition of Decode Genetics at length, emphasizing the imperative role collaboration plays in translational research—an interdisciplinary research style that is currently guiding the industry. Bradway noted there has been recent feverish collaboration as government withdraws more funding for basic research. We are seeing this withdrawal because of a decades-long steady monetary decline. More investment in genetics can reverse this by quickening the drug development process and making it more efficacious. Per Bradway’s account, Amgen is looking ahead to identify and develop therapies based on the genetic and molecular understanding of a disease and its pathway. As industry at large is seen further reducing its commitment to discovery research, Amgen proclaims it is not shrinking back.</p>
<p>Scangos’ account provided insider details into Biogen’s past and current Phase 2 and 3 trials for ALS, MS and AD therapies. Scangos praised the role academic collaborations have had in driving the talent, direction, and mission of successful biotechnology research and development. Scangos also shed light on Biogen’s biggest concern for the next half decade—the current environmental context that medical research operates in. Thoughtful public policy will be necessary to fulfill the potential of this pivotal time in medical history—with aligned talent, resources, and a greater understanding of neurologic diseases than ever before.</p>
<p><strong><em>Secretary One-on-One</em></strong></p>
<p><em><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1501" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-300x200.jpg" alt="Sylvia Mathews Burwell" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A7296-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><br />
</em>The one-on-one conversation with Honorable Sylvia Matthews Burwell, Secretary of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, echoed Scangos’ glimpse into the importance of public policy. Secretary Burwell emphasized the similar priorities all entities hold—affordable, accessible, life-changing therapies for patients. By changing health care pay systems, implementing integrated care systems, and moving forward with data collection, analytics, and protection, the Department of Health and Human Services is optimistic about the next phases of neuroscience care and beyond.</p>
<p><em><strong>Neurostimulation: First Line Therapy?</strong></em><br />
What is neuromodulation and why does it work? Neuromodulation is the use of various kinds of electric signals to restore the brain to a more normal state. It is a broad and emerging field; we are on the verge of a revolution with treating diseases such a Parkinson&#8217;s, epilepsy and OCD. This type of treatment has been around for decades but has recently re-emerged through new findings in neuroscience research.</p>
<p>Speakers said that in the past, neuromodulation treatments worked, but nobody knew why. Although the field is much more developed now, patients are still hesitant to embrace this technology due to its highly invasive nature. Panelists mentioned that up to 15 percent of Parkinson’s patients receive these implants, but there still needs to be additional education and a shift in mindset in order for this type of treatment to be more widely adopted – a challenge that may be overcome with time. ​</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Forum &#8211; Day 1 Recap</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/world-forum-day-1-recap/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 13:50:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1484</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Partners HealthCare kicked off its inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum in Boston on April 27 with a truly international presence, bringing together over 1,000 attendees from 18 countries to discuss and advance the state of neuroscience research, patient care, and delivery. The first day of this three-day event also highlighted the role of collaboration and <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Partners HealthCare kicked off its inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum in Boston on April 27 with a truly international presence, bringing together over 1,000 attendees from 18 countries to discuss and advance the state of neuroscience research, patient care, and delivery. The first day of this three-day event also highlighted the role of collaboration and partnering across stakeholders in venture capital, academia, life sciences, and health care to ensure financial sustainability amidst increasing cost pressures and constraints in funding.</p>
<p>Neurological diseases are particularly prominent and represent a huge, unaddressed disease burden across global societies, and today’s panels provided a multifaceted view of the current state of care for neurological diseases, accompanied by bold proposals for what the future setting of neurocare will entail.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Discovery Cafe, Welcome</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1487" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-300x200.jpg" alt="Discovery Cafe - 1" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6249-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>The day kicked off on when attendees gathered over lunch for a roundtable discussion on a specific topic, moderated by a champion in that field, called the Discovery Cafe. Topics ranged from psychiatric care to information systems and how they all can contribute to innovation in the neurosciences. Rich, interdisciplinary discussion flowed among clinicians, industry experts, policymakers, and researchers. The Discovery Cafe provided a platform to transform mingling and networking into purposeful interaction between fellow attendees.</p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1488" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-300x200.jpg" alt="Welcome - 1" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6396-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>Attendees were officially ushered into their upcoming three days of neurological innovation by CEO of Partners HealthCare, David Torchiana, M.D., and Chief Academic Officer of Partners HealthCare, Anne Klibanski, M.D., as well as by Boston Mayor Marty Walsh. A significant fraction of Partners HealthCare’s $1.5 billion enterprise is work in the neurosciences. The audience was called to action to push the frontiers of medicine against the backdrop of world-renowned facilities, scientists, and clinicians that is Boston.</p>
<p><strong>Neurocare, Neuromarkets, and Neuro Challenges </strong><br />
The day’s first panel, “Neurocare, Neuromarkets, and Neuro Challenges,” cited early detection and prophylactic care as key needs across Alzheimer’s and psychiatric care. Scott Rauch, President and Psychiatrist in Chief at McLean Hospital, stated it’s the rule rather than the exception that patients are suffering from psychiatric diseases for years before they are detected. These observations, however, were tempered amidst real-world reservations from patients, who may not want to know about genetic predispositions or had privacy concerns amidst proposals for earlier screening and detection.</p>
<p>Clinical neuroscience leaders across Partners HealthCare were called to dive into the past, present, and future of diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease (AD) to share how far we have come in the field and how very much there is still left to discover. A common thread throughout was that stigma is stalling. The medicalization of psychiatric illnesses has been a remarkable jump forward &#8211; clinicians are now viewing bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, etc., as diseases with an originating pathology like how we view hypertension or diabetes. We are now seeing the beginning of stigma erosion in public figures and celebrities stepping forward to advocate for these illnesses.</p>
<p>With this new clinical perspective comes the challenge of screening. When will AD be uniformly screened, like colon cancer? To reach patients at the primary care level is key to early intervention. It is widely understood now that changes in the brain due to AD occur decades before symptoms first appear. Engaging at-risk patients earlier and understanding how inflammation in the immune system contributes to its spread will be of note in the future of AD care.</p>
<p>In neurosurgery, advances are more technical but no less exciting. There is more precision than ever before in imaging and in the miniaturization of instruments. Gels and focused ultrasounds are able to cross the blood-brain barrier and deliver the appropriate amount of drugs to a specific location in the brain. These advances contribute to the minimization of collateral brain damage during surgery. As neurosurgery becomes safer and more seamless, we will see patients with better outcomes.</p>
<p>Not only are we able to enter the brain with newfound surgical specificity, but we are also now at the advent of specificity in neurogenetics. The future of neurocare will be linking outcomes and treatments to the genotypes of patients. Researchers are beginning to acknowledge the overlap that many of these neurodegenerative diseases share in similar genetic predispositions. This can be translated into clinical trial design by finding out how successful patients are different genetically and then designing the next trial based on that data. Lowering the burden of becoming involved in clinical trials is key to the advancement of research. Another challenge to neurocare is how to expand access to treatment. Telemedicine plays a big role with programs such as cognitive behavioral therapy being available online. Our personal devices like phones and tablets hold the answer to remote monitoring. It is how we contextualize this deluge of “big data” that will shape the trajectory of the neuromarket in upcoming years.</p>
<p><strong>“Over the Horizon: Witnessing Disruption of Neurocare”</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1489" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-300x200.jpg" alt="Over the Horizon - 1" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6594-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><br />
The day’s second panel, “Over the Horizon: Witnessing the Disruption of Neurocare,” generated bold predictions across industry and public research organizations, proposing an array of traditional therapeutics, electroceutical, brain-machine interface approaches to treat human disease and augment lifestyles, even repositioning the nervous system as the vehicle to deliver and refine treatment for patients. As Geoffrey Ling, Director of Biological Technologies Office at DARPA pointed out, experiments highlighting cognitive control of prosthetic limbs point to a potential applications that could surpass the limits of our sensory organs and other exogenous tools to improve patient cognition and lifestyles, especially in states of frailty observed later in life.</p>
<p>This provocative panel leapt into novel ideas that the panelists believe are just at the cusp of neurological innovation. These neuro-forecasters pooled their collective knowledge from biotechnology and big pharma to present the most cutting-edge and controversial of work. The audience was advised to abandon any preconceived notions on how innovation works, citing that humans did not know that cell phones would be so ingrained into our lifestyle a decade ago. Panelists pushed that in the future of the patient-empowered age, everyone will be sequencing their genome, even from birth. The best drugs will then be gene-modifiers, and the concept of a “drug” could completely vanish as combined strategies make their way into therapeutics and care plans. Clinicians will soon be prescribing drugs with apps or drugs with software. The concept of a “dose” will change as we add different interfaces into neurocare.</p>
<p>One of these novel “neural interfaces” is the concept of “electroceuticals,” or devices that deliver electrical stimulation at the level of peripheral nerves. These exquisitely specific devices will be smaller than a grain of rice and allow us to control our neurocircuitry. It is up to investigators of the future to map the neurocircuitry of diseases. The concept that the central nervous system is synergistic with pathology throughout the body is one that may be difficult for clinicians to adapt to. For example, it is clear that diabetes is a metabolic disorder but how clear is it that it is a neurological one? Imagine the possibility of treating an illness with “information” in addition to drugs.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) may be characteristic of science fiction movies, but is nothing to fear, but rather embrace. The Stone Age and Iron Age were eras of tool adaptation, and so the expected path is that the Digital Age will move onto AI as we “adapt” to the synergy of brain and machine. By doing this, we are “liberating our bodies” and allowing our cognitive capacity to accomplish more. Our future lies in the “Internet of things,” or rather than having exogenous control in the form of cellphones, tablets, etc., we will have internal cognitive control over our environment. This is not a new concept; brain-controlled prosthetics are allowing amputees to control limbs. Phones and computers may be a thing of the past one day, and “smart” environments will take their place.</p>
<p>Along with enhancing our environments, enhancing the normal human condition is pushing the frontiers of medicine. Becoming bionic may mean unprecedented longevity for today’s youth. To achieve this. we must understand what is the “average” condition and why is it that we age and become ill. Have our genes not adapted to today’s environment and lifestyle? If so, perhaps we can identify those genes that cause disease and aging and “turn them off.” Ethical issues will be an obstacle to many of these radical ideas and must be addressed before becoming mainstream.</p>
<p>So, what must happen in order for these concepts to be implemented in the clinical setting? Building the technological platforms and understanding the revolutionary biology must happen simultaneously. Industry stakeholders have to own this work in order for it to make it into practice. As the population grows older, public pressure mounts with the heavy societal burdens of neurological disease.</p>
<p>For both the research and innovation communities, key challenges and questions arise: Why is therapeutic development usually a second career? Why is it not viewed more urgently in the minds of clinicians? What barriers are holding them back from tapping into this rich field? For innovators trying to propel disruptive interventions like electroceuticals into the care space, what will it take for consumers and patients to choose devices over drugs? IUDs and implants prove to be the most effective contraceptive method, yet pills are the most widely preferred method today. Will the idea of “invasiveness” change over time as the body interacts more with technology?</p>
<p>Only time can answer these pressing questions on the minds of today’s innovators and researchers. Biology is becoming more of a quantitative science. “Coding” our nerves and gene editing has the potential to become a universal standard of treatment. “Cognitive resilience,” or the fielding of symptoms of AD, for example, can become a reality and greatly impact the quality of life of patients. At the intersection of therapeutics and technology lie a wealth of knowledge that we do not yet know how to harvest.</p>
<p><strong>Transformation and Innovation: Conflict? Collision? Opportunity?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1490" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-300x200.jpg" alt="Transformation and Innovation - 1" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6603-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><br />
Chief Executives from provider, pharmaceutical, and medical device stakeholders took the floor to highlight stakeholder considerations, opportunities, and needs in the face of a decrease in inflation adjusted NIH funding and population health burdens. As Jeff Leiden, M.D., Ph.D., CEO of Vertex, noted, the irony is that the science has never been better, but the funding has never been worse.</p>
<p>While undertones in funding and an increasingly difficult operating environment where apparent throughout the day, the panelists shared a universal optimism for the current state of medicine and an excitement in the potential advances to come, often pointing to current market forces as motivators for improvements in treatment and care. As Leiden noted, the health care community has a great story to tell when it comes to the value and impact that the system brings to society; we just need to focus on communicating that story to the public.</p>
<p>Posted by Angelica Recierdo, Thomas Martz, and Alessandra Maahs</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Day 1 of the World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 12:39:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1482</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The almost $700 billion annual spend in neurodegenerative diseases tells a story of a global community struck by an array of stubborn neurological conditions and challenged by drug discovery, delivery, care, regulatory protocols, and economic and organizational practices serving at cross-purposes. Yet, there was something inspirational and I dare say hopeful about the presenters’ opinions <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-1491 size-medium" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-300x200.jpg" alt="Neurocare - 1" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-300x200.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-768x512.jpg 768w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-150x100.jpg 150w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-120x80.jpg 120w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/5H8A6515-93x62.jpg 93w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>The almost $700 billion annual spend in neurodegenerative diseases tells a story of a global community struck by an array of stubborn neurological conditions and challenged by drug discovery, delivery, care, regulatory protocols, and economic and organizational practices serving at cross-purposes. Yet, there was something inspirational and I dare say hopeful about the presenters’ opinions of what’s to come.</p>
<p>Technology, transparency, and passion appeared central to the secret sauce. Much was stated about the power of smart devices allowing the organic evolution of large data sets to evolve and yield insight and action in a scalable fashion not seen till now.</p>
<p>Second, transparency, or specifically data and process transparency, appeared thematic as another dimension supporting progress. That is, having enhanced access and data deployment through analytics, machine interfaces, and control mechanisms further influenced interventions. This may, in cases, lead to more precise mapping, stimulating, manipulating, and modulating of circuits, genes, and varied organs in a more predictive, synergistic fashion &#8212; yielding greater value and utility.</p>
<p>Additionally, the collective process and arrangement of organized inquiry, aggregation, experimentation, and delivery may interestingly be compared to a very different but similarly transparent process.</p>
<p>In the food and beverage industry, the fast-casual restaurant segment is very popular. Chipotle Restaurant, the leader in this segment, allows diners to self-select and view the assembling of an array of diverse ingredients for a given order. The interaction effects of the employee and customer publicly engaging in the co-design and build effort yields more satisfaction, efficiency, and taste with both creator and consumer, as noted in the restaurant surveys. Similarly, in health care research, such increased process transparency is no less immaterial in the discovery-delivery value chain.</p>
<p>Third, it seems the very human quality of passion and / or emotion, can also play an out-sized role in the direction and dynamics of next gen neuroscience. Many stories about the fear surrounding Alzheimer’s is self-evident here. As described, we have all heard of some version of the hapless wonderer in the parking lot seeking their car, keys or both, much to one’s frustration. This example, perhaps associated with Alzheimer’s, can easily and obviously be substituted with other neurodegenerative diseases, as well.</p>
<p>On the hopeful side, passion was referenced as a motivator that has led to an activist public seeking answers. Their intent has further engaged some to experiment in varied ways that on occasion has yielded surprising, timely, and consequential data.</p>
<p>While there is much to hope for, there are equally many daunting challenges requiring attention. Certainly, as always, understanding the fundamental root causes, relationships, pathways, and protocols of the disease state is central. However, just as daunting on a more macro-level is the institutional – organizational arrangement in moving beyond silos to varied operating forms of collaboration, coordination, “co-opitition,” and disruption.</p>
<p>The clarion call for innovation at a cellular or genomic level can also be matched with one for social innovation. That is the experimentation for team and organizational architectures to have more appropriately employed decision rights, accountability mechanisms, resource management, and role agility &#8212; all in the service of empowering knowledge creation and application in a more expedient, practical and generative fashion when called for.</p>
<p>Finally, economic innovation is perhaps recognized as an equally stubborn yet central player in creating an optimal future for balancing the incentives for payers, payees, and providers. Agile business and operating models, governance mechanisms, and investment models will need to be created and adjusted as the field continues to mature at different stages of capability and practice.</p>
<p>Posted By Mark Sullivan, PhD</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/new-hopes-for-alzheimers-disease-featured-at-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 16:41:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1478</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum Six Reasons why the Anti-Amyloid Treatment in Asymptomatic Alzheimer’s study (the &#8220;A4 study&#8221;) with Reisa Sperling, MD, BWH, Director of Clinical Research, Memory Disorders Unit, Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital is making Strides 1. The novel concept of treating patients before they are symptomatic Instead <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>New Hopes for Alzheimer’s disease featured at World Medical Innovation Forum</strong></p>
<p>Six Reasons why the Anti-Amyloid Treatment in Asymptomatic Alzheimer’s study (the &#8220;A4 study&#8221;) with Reisa Sperling, MD, BWH, Director of Clinical Research, Memory Disorders Unit,<br />
Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital is making Strides</p>
<p><strong>1. The novel concept of treating patients before they are symptomatic</strong></p>
<p>Instead of waiting until patients develop full blown Alzheimer’s disease, the A4 study has been proactive. The A4 study targets older individuals with evidence of early Alzheimer’s changes in their brain but who do not yet have symptoms of Alzheimer’s disease, in hopes of preventing memory decline. This is the first time in history of AD research that a prevention trial has been undertaken in asymptomatic individuals identified with biomarker evidence of Alzheimer’s disease.</p>
<p><strong>2. The use of an anti-amyloid antibody</strong></p>
<p>The humanized monoclonal antibody, solanezumab, which has already be testing in two Phase 3 trials at the stage of Alzheimers’ dementia, binds to soluble forms of amyloid and can help its clearance of it from the brain. The previous trials in dementia patients showed some modest evidence of slowing of decline in the mildest subgroup. The hope is treating 5-10 years earlier with this antibody can bend the curve of decline.</p>
<p><strong>3. It’s empowering patients to manage their health and potential risk for developing AD</strong></p>
<p>The A4 study has made people more aware of options for treatment and potential cures in the works. Alzheimer&#8217;s disease is not a death sentence and clinicians and researchers are working hard through this trial and other to get closer to finding a cure.</p>
<p><strong>4.It’s getting people talking about Alzheimer’s disease (more people learning about what Alzheimer’s actually is, informing families at risk, communities, etc.)</strong></p>
<p>Almost everyone knows someone, or has a friend who has known someone affected by Alzheimer’s disease. More and more people are hearing the words “Alzheimer’s disease” in conversation but do not exactly know what it means. These trials are giving the disease much more press, and increasing awareness. This is beneficial in many aspects such as fundraising for research and recruiting people for this study.</p>
<p><strong>5. It involves collaborations</strong></p>
<p>The A4 trial is sponsored by a public-private partnership involving the National Institutes of Health, Eli Lilly, and several philanthropic organizations. The A4 study is also working with other prevention trial efforts in genetic at-risk populations around the world to ensure they can learn as much as possible from these trials.</p>
<p><strong>6. It emphasizes its urgency</strong></p>
<p>Most people are not aware of the urgency of action for Alzheimer’s disease. One of nine people over the age of 65 has the disease, and as our population ages, Alzheimer’s disease is becoming a public health epidemic. If we do not do something about it, this disease has the potential to bankrupt our healthcare system. It is critical to increase awareness and send the message something that can be done to cure Alzheimer’s if we act now. Attend this year’s World Medical Innovation Forum on April 27-29, 2015. Click here (medforum17.wpengine.com) to learn more.</p>
<p>Piece by Alessandra Maahs, BWH iHub</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Charles Czeisler Talks NASA &#038; Sleep Science</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/dr-charles-czeisler-talks-nasa-sleep-science/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meaghan Doherty]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1451</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON &#8212; Dr. Charles Czeisler, MD, PhD, is up to some incredible things. He and his colleagues at Brigham and Women’s Hospital recently received NASA’s Johnson Space Center Director’s Innovation Award in Houston for their work on light systems, which will help astronauts adjust their Circadian clocks. He’s also presenting at this year’s Partners HealthCare <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON &#8212; Dr. Charles Czeisler, MD, PhD, is up to some incredible things. He and his colleagues at Brigham and Women’s Hospital recently received NASA’s Johnson Space Center Director’s Innovation Award in Houston for their work on light systems, which will help astronauts adjust their Circadian clocks. He’s also presenting at this year’s <a href="https://medtechboston.medstro.com/events/world-medical-innovation-forum-neurosciences/" target="_blank">Partners HealthCare World Medical Innovation Forum</a>, on April 27 – 29, 2015.<br />
<script src="https://apis.google.com/_/scs/apps-static/_/js/k=oz.gapi.en.NWMUTAs0kOE.O/m=auth/exm=plusone/rt=j/sv=1/d=1/ed=1/am=IQ/rs=AGLTcCPxj8CQhcqlMkFMk_msXSwX7g5HPA/t=zcms/cb=gapi.loaded_1" async=""></script></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Howard Weiner: A Doctor on a Mission to Cure MS</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/howard-weiner-a-doctor-on-a-mission-to-cure-ms/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 16:27:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meaghan Doherty]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BOSTON]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1450</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON &#8212; It was during his early days as a doctor that Howard Weiner, MD, director and co-founder of the Partners Multiple Sclerosis Center at Brigham &#38; Women’s Hospital, treated a young father who had recently experienced a very bad multiple sclerosis (MS) attack. Weiner immediately identified with his patient: he was about the same age, <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON &#8212; It was during his early days as a doctor that Howard Weiner, MD, director and co-founder of the <a href="http://www.partnersmscenter.org/" target="_blank">Partners Multiple Sclerosis Center</a> at <a href="http://www.brighamandwomens.org/" target="_blank">Brigham &amp; Women’s Hospital</a>, treated a young father who had recently experienced a very bad multiple sclerosis (MS) attack. Weiner immediately identified with his patient: he was about the same age, and he also had two boys. It hit him on an emotional level that there was no cure for MS.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spotlighting Innovation at Our Inaugural Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/spotlighting-innovation-at-our-inaugural-forum/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 16:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum16.wpengine.com/?p=1441</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Throughout the United States, every phase of healthcare is being fundamentally restructured. As these changes take place, the need for disruptive research and applied innovation will remain an enduring priority. Partners HealthCare, as the largest single academic research entity, is convening leaders from around the globe to consider the future of collaborative innovation as part <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1442" src="http://medforum16.wpengine.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321.jpg" alt="Spotlighting Innovation" width="550" height="321" srcset="https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321.jpg 550w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321-300x175.jpg 300w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321-171x100.jpg 171w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321-137x80.jpg 137w, https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Partners_FORUM_2015_LOGO_550x321-106x62.jpg 106w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></p>
<p>Throughout the United States, every phase of healthcare is being fundamentally restructured. As these changes take place, the need for disruptive research and applied innovation will remain an enduring priority. Partners HealthCare, as the largest single academic research entity, is convening leaders from around the globe to consider the future of collaborative innovation as part of the inaugural World Medical Innovation Forum.</p>
<p>The event, an international gathering of more than 1,000 senior decision-makers from the life sciences, investment, clinical, entrepreneurial and academic communities, will be taking place in Boston from April 27-29, 2015. The Forum is rooted in the belief that no matter how greatly the health care industry transforms, health care providers remain committed to working together to improve patient lives through innovation.</p>
<p>The focus for this first World Forum will be the neurosciences. The Forum will present an unprecedented opportunity for senior executives, investors, entrepreneurs, physicians and scientists on the forefront of medical advancement to discuss the most compelling advances in neuroscience technology, care and research, as well as the importance of innovation throughout health care.</p>
<p>Keynote speakers will include CEOs from some of the most important companies in the neurosciences and healthcare in general, such as General Electric, Aetna, Amgen, Biogen Idec, Boston Scientific, Genzyme, Vertex Pharmaceuticals and many more. Also keynoting the Forum are dozens of internationally recognized Partners’ leaders and Harvard Medical School Faculty such as Atul Gawande, M.D., and Rudy Tanzi, Ph.D.</p>
<p>More than 100 expert speakers will discuss advances and unmet needs in areas such as multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s diseases, depression, schizophrenia, autism, stroke and sleep disorders. The Forum will also highlight new tools and interventions in genome editing, gene therapy, neurostimulation, neurodegeneration, population management, neuroimaging and neurological biomarkers.</p>
<p>In addition to examining the cutting-edge issues in the field, the Forum will feature the “Disruptive Dozen” – 12 emerging technologies with the potential to revolutionize the neurosciences over the next decade.</p>
<p>Through its unprecedented roster of presenters and top attendees, the hope is that meaningful engagement throughout the World Forum will spark the new partnerships needed to address longstanding unmet needs and lay the groundwork for future collaborations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Forum Will Draw Executives</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/world-forum-will-draw-executives/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 16:05:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=1360</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Sylvia Mathews Burwell, the US secretary of Health and Human Services, has a big job. Right now, for example, that involves being named in a lawsuit over the future of health care reform before the US Supreme Court. But Burwell can escape the anti-Obamacare vibes for a bit on her upcoming visit to health reform-friendly <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b class="b">Sylvia Mathews Burwell</b>, the <b class="b">US secretary of Health and Human Services</b>, has a big job.<br />
<script src="http://dnn506yrbagrg.cloudfront.net/pages/scripts/0014/1023.js?396328" async="true" type="text/javascript"></script></p>
<div id="contain">
<article class="article">
<div class="article-body">
<div class="article-text">
<p>Right now, for example, that involves being named in a lawsuit over the future of health care reform before the US Supreme Court.</p>
<p>But Burwell can escape the anti-Obamacare vibes for a bit on her upcoming visit to health reform-friendly Massachusetts.</p>
<p>She is among an elite group of health and science leaders who will speak next month at the <b class="b">W</b><b class="b">orld Medical Innovation Forum</b>, a new event sponsored by <b class="b">Partners HealthCare.</b></p>
<p>Partners, the system that includes<b class="b"> Massachusetts General</b> and <b class="b">Brigham and Women’s</b> hospitals, developed a program featuring a list of headliners who are at the forefront of research and innovation. The list of speakers includes high-profile local chief executives: <b class="b">Jeffrey Leiden</b> of Boston’s <b class="b">Vertex Pharmaceuticals</b>, <b class="b">Michael Mahoney</b> of Marlborough-based <b class="b">Boston Scientific</b>,<b class="b"> Deborah Dunsire</b> of Watertown-based <b class="b">Forum Pharmaceuticals</b>, and from Cambridge, <b class="b">David Meeker</b> of <b class="b">Genzyme,</b> and <b class="b">George Scangos</b> of <b class="b">Biogen Idec.</b></p>
<p>Also on the schedule is <b class="b">Ann Romney</b>, who is the wife of the former Massachusetts governor and presidential candidate, and an ambassador for multiple sclerosis patients.</p>
<p>Brigham last year named its <b class="b">Center for Neurologic Diseases</b> for Romney, who was diagnosed with MS in 1998.</p>
<p>The innovation forum, slated for April 27 to 29 at the <b class="b">Westin Copley Place</b> hotel, will be centered on neuroscience.</p>
<p>Of course, being sponsored by the state’s biggest health system, the event will include plenty of speakers with Partners on their name tags.</p>
</div>
</div>
</article>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Partners HealthCare Announces Keynote Speakers for the 2015 World Medical Innovation Forum</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/partners-healthcare-announces-keynote-speakers-for-the-2015-world-medical-innovation-forum/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 22:58:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[WMIF Admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=1269</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BOSTON &#8212; Partners HealthCare today announced the keynote speakers, including several of the health industry’s most well-known and respected chief executives, for the first annual World Medical Innovation Forum™, which will bring together more than 1,000 international decision-makers from the life sciences, health care, academic and investment communities on April 27-29, 2015, in Boston to <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BOSTON &#8212; Partners HealthCare today announced the keynote speakers, including several of the health industry’s most well-known and respected chief executives, for the first annual <a class="icon " href="http://cts.businesswire.com/ct/CT?id=smartlink&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fmedforum17.wpengine.com%2F&amp;esheet=51045489&amp;newsitemid=20150224005677&amp;lan=en-US&amp;anchor=World+Medical+Innovation+Forum%E2%84%A2&amp;index=1&amp;md5=5ed5aa5afbb320e497f0d7326b5c6c1c" target="_new">World Medical Innovation Forum<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/11/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a>, which will bring together more than 1,000 international decision-makers from the life sciences, health care, academic and investment communities on April 27-29, 2015, in Boston to discuss the most compelling advances in neuroscience technology, care and research.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ann Romney campaigning hard for medical research</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/ann-romney-campaigning-hard-for-medical-research/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 16:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Transmit Studio]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=665</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[BELMONT — Ann Romney knows a lot about political campaigns. Win or lose, there’s one thing you gain for sure: a network of people with an awful lot of money. They couldn’t put her husband, Mitt, in the White House, but she’s now hoping everyone will get behind her to launch the Ann Romney Center <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BELMONT — Ann Romney knows a lot about political campaigns. Win or lose, there’s one thing you gain for sure: a network of people with an awful lot of money.</p>
<p>They couldn’t put her husband, Mitt, in the White House, but she’s now hoping everyone will get behind her to launch the <a class="a" href="http://www.bwhannromneycenter.org/">Ann Romney Center for Neurologic Diseases</a> at Brigham and Women’s Hospital. Her goal is to create a new model for research and funding, setting out to raise $50 million over the next year to help find treatments and cures for five conditions: multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s, Lou Gehrig’s (ALS), Parkinson’s, and brain tumors.</p>
<p>The Romneys are seeding the center with what Ann calls a “substantial gift.” And I trust that it is big. Before Mitt’s two failed presidential bids and before he served as our governor, he made a fortune as founder of Bain Capital, the Boston buyout firm.</p>
<p>This is hardly a vanity project for Mrs. Romney. She has lived for 16 years with MS, a chronic disease of the immune system in which nerves deteriorate, causing symptoms as severe as paralysis. Her doctor, Howard Weiner, is at the Brigham and the idea for a new center came two years ago following a routine visit. Romney’s MS, initially treated with steroids, has been in remission for more than a decade and is now managed by a healthy diet and exercise.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Breakthrough Replicates Human Brain Cells for Use in Alzheimer’s Research</title>
		<link>https://davekuhar.github.io/partners-wmif-2017/breakthrough-replicates-human-brain-cells-for-use-in-alzheimers-research/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 16:00:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Transmit Studio]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://medforum17.wpengine.com/?p=667</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For the first time, and to the astonishment of many of their colleagues, researchers created what they call Alzheimer’s in a Dish — a petri dish with human brain cells that develop the telltale structures of Alzheimer’s disease. In doing so, they resolved a longstanding problem of how to study Alzheimer’s and search for drugs <span class="continue-link">...</span>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="story-continues-1" class="story-body-text story-content" data-para-count="435" data-total-count="435">For the first time, and to the astonishment of many of their colleagues, researchers created what they call <a class="meta-classifier" title="In-depth reference and news articles about Alzheimer's Disease." href="http://health.nytimes.com/health/guides/disease/alzheimers-disease/overview.html?inline=nyt-classifier">Alzheimer’s</a> in a Dish — a petri dish with human brain cells that develop the telltale structures of Alzheimer’s disease. In doing so, they resolved a longstanding problem of how to study Alzheimer’s and search for drugs to treat it; the best they had until now were mice that developed an imperfect form of the disease.</p>
<p class="story-body-text story-content" data-para-count="479" data-total-count="914">The key to their success, said the lead researcher, Rudolph E. Tanzi of <a title="More articles about Massachusetts General Hospital" href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/m/massachusetts_general_hospital/index.html?inline=nyt-org">Massachusetts General Hospital</a> in Boston, was a suggestion by his colleague Doo Yeon Kim to grow human brain cells in a gel, where they formed networks as in an actual brain. They gave the neurons genes for Alzheimer’s disease. Within weeks they saw the hard Brillo-like clumps known as plaques and then the twisted spaghetti-like coils known as tangles — the defining features of Alzheimer’s disease.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
